<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>iilab - Innovative Technology For Social Impact</title>
        <link>https://iilab.org</link>
        <description><![CDATA[iilab harnesses information innovation to help your social good initiatives improve their human impact.]]></description>
        <atom:link href="https://iilab.org/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2015 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Ten recommendations to make the water sector more resilient - open data and citizen stewardship</title>
    <link>https://iilab.org/news/2015-12-01-recommendations-water-sector-open-data-citizen-stewardship.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>How do we make a difference to water resilience? Today’s report, published by Ofwat and compiled by the independent Water Resilience Task and Finish Group, contains ten UK-focussed recommendations for improving water resilience.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The recommendations in brief are:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Agree a shared definition of resilience for the sector.</li>
<li>Increase public engagement and education</li>
<li>Ensure clear routes for funding legitimate resilience measures</li>
<li>Ensure coherent planning for resilience at both a national and regional level</li>
<li>Establish wastewater, sewerage and drainage plans</li>
<li>Improve understanding of risk and failure</li>
<li>Ensure services are resilient under different water sector structures</li>
<li>Develop benchmarking, standards and metrics</li>
<li>Ensure existing plans are stress-tested</li>
<li>Establish a water and wastewater resilience action group</li>
</ol>
<p>You can <a href="http://www.ofwat.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/rpt_com20151201resiliencetaskfinish.pdf">read and download the report from the Ofwat website</a>.</p>
<h2 id="open-data-and-citizen-stewardship-of-water-resources">Open data and citizen stewardship of water resources</h2>
<p>I’ve been part of the Task and Finish group over the last year, and you may remember that <a href="https://iilab.org/news/2015-07-28-uk-water-resilience.html">we launched a call for participation earlier this year</a>. Thank you to everyone who contributed. I’m thrilled that the recommendations contain calls for open data and greater citizen agency have been included in the report:</p>
<p><em>2. Increase public engagement and education When: 2015 - 2020 Lead: Water companies and governments Involved: All sector and non sector partners, including stakeholders and third parties Using a common definition, or set of definitions, there is a need to engage the wider public, particularly in relation to risk, and to develop a common understanding of the acceptability of risk. This engagement should be twofold. Firstly it should involve the provision of pertinent information on a wide scale on an ongoing basis, with the aim of enhancing public understanding of water systems. Secondly it should aim to ensure this information is transformed into active engagement (which will lead to positive environmental behaviour) - the public should be given an active role in resilience, both in terms of adaptation and mitigation. The action to deliver this recommendation sits with all bodies in the sector. But it sits primarily with water companies who must undertake much more active engagement and with governments who, whilst they are unlikely to do any public outreach in this area, must reinstate areas where they have removed information provision, like the reintroduction of the water cycle as a key element of the national curriculum. The water sector should, where possible, continue to increase access to data, subject to commercial confidentiality and security exemptions. The sector strategic dashboard currently being developed by water companies, regulators and other stakeholders could be a helpful contribution to facilitating that access. More open data would assist better public understanding and engagement and could promote innovation and understanding and increase resilience through crowd sourced solutions and oversight.</em></p>
<p>and</p>
<p><em>6. Improve the understanding of risk and failure When: 2015 - 2020 Lead: Environment Agency, Natural Resources Wales, water companies There needs to be broad discussion, involving all parties including customers, leading to agreement on the level of service which should be planned for in each area. This would be based on better understanding and communication of the risks faced by the water sector, of the costs of failure, and of the costs and benefits of measures to avert, manage and recover from failure. Coping strategies for dealing with ‘beyond resilience’ emergencies (black swan events) also need to be agreed, in advance of their occurrence. Progress in these matters will enable water companies to focus on the risks to critical assets and services, and to plan for the effective delivery of services in critical conditions, with a mandate from their customers and society, and from their regulators and government. Another requirement is an appreciation by all that some failures will occur, notwithstanding best plans being laid and large investment being made; for example, expecting zero leakage and never having supply interruptions is unhelpful thinking. Risk could also be better understood and dealt with through more open data, enabling wider scrutiny of water and wastewater management. This could link to the sector strategic dashboard that is currently under development.</em></p>
<h2 id="get-your-hands-wet">Get your hands wet</h2>
<p>These points around facilitating citizen stewardship of water and increased open data from the water sector, while hard-won, are backed up by current academic literature on resilience, and a systems map that we’ve been working on on the kumu platform. They’re issues we’ve also discussed previously, for instance in <a href="https://iilab.org/news/2014-11-02-open-droplet-lote4.html">our session at LOTE4 The Stewardship</a>. If open data and citizen stewardship of water are important to you, please add your voice and action to making these changes real. We’re particularly interested to hear about projects where there is community stewardship of resources. <script type="text/javascript">
<!--
h='&#x69;&#x69;&#108;&#x61;&#98;&#46;&#x6f;&#114;&#x67;';a='&#64;';n='&#x63;&#x6f;&#110;&#116;&#x61;&#x63;&#116;';e=n+a+h;
document.write('<a h'+'ref'+'="ma'+'ilto'+':'+e+'" clas'+'s="em' + 'ail">'+'Get in touch with us here at iilab'+'<\/'+'a'+'>');
// -->
</script><noscript>&#x47;&#x65;&#116;&#32;&#x69;&#110;&#32;&#116;&#x6f;&#x75;&#x63;&#104;&#32;&#x77;&#x69;&#116;&#104;&#32;&#x75;&#x73;&#32;&#104;&#x65;&#114;&#x65;&#32;&#x61;&#116;&#32;&#x69;&#x69;&#108;&#x61;&#98;&#32;&#40;&#x63;&#x6f;&#110;&#116;&#x61;&#x63;&#116;&#32;&#x61;&#116;&#32;&#x69;&#x69;&#108;&#x61;&#98;&#32;&#100;&#x6f;&#116;&#32;&#x6f;&#114;&#x67;&#x29;</noscript>, or <a href="http://twitter.com/home?status=Calling%20for%20#opendata%20and%20#peoplepower%20for%20#water%20#resilience%20cc%20@iilab%20https://bit.ly/resilience-water">tweet this post</a>.</p>
<p>We’re still working on the water resilience systems map. A static version is included in the report, and shown above. We’d like to invite you to <a href="https://kumu.io/iilab/ofwat-resilience-systems-map">contribute to building the map further by collaborating with us on kumu</a>. We’re sure there are more insights we can get out of this mapping - ones that will be relevant globally.</p>
<p><a href="https://kumu.io/iilab/ofwat-resilience-systems-map">Collaborate on the Water Resilience Systems map on kumu</a>.</p>
<h2 id="water-resilience---what-the-papers-say">Water resilience - what the papers say</h2>
<p>Meanwhile, if you have a more academic interest in water resilience, I compiled this literature review for the report. While the report is now closed, our interest in this topic is still as keen as ever. Please join the conversation if you have feedback that we can move forward with. Resilience of water systems</p>
<p>Like any complex system, resilience of water systems can be defined in terms of their response to specific threats over time (Haimes, 2009). Many factors are implicated in water resilience (Matthews, 2015), such as water scarcity for both green and blue water, water quality, flooding, waste water, salinisation, and economic scarcity where social resources required to successfully adapt to physical water scarcity fall short (Ohlsson, 2000), and it is the factors that feed into their provision that determines the resilience of the system with respect to a particular threat. A distinction can be made between man-made resilience issues, and those that occur naturally - for instance water scarcity as a result of natural conditions of low water availability in comparison to water scarcity mainly induced by a large human demand relative to natural availability (which can also happen in water abundant areas) (Schyns et al, 2015). This is an engineering resilience perspective, and one which has been largely adopted by the UK in its approach to resilience more broadly, and in this report. In the literature, alternative views of resilience exist, for instance a more socio-ecological view of resilience looks at resilience of a system in terms of the repurcussions on both human needs and ecosystem needs, seeing them as intrinsically linked. In such cases resilience is defined not as how well a system recovers from or adapts to events, but in terms of “the amount of disturbance a linked social-ecological system can absorb before reorganizing into a new state characterized by a different set of processes and structures.” (Garmestani et al. 2014).</p>
<p>In order to solve resilience problems in such a complex system, it is necessary to move away from focussing on components in the system to looking at the system’s interconnectedness (Helbing et al, 2012), including links to systems that may be seen as discrete, such as the electricity network (Matthews, 2015) or a country’s legal framework (Garmestani et al., 2014). Approaches to water resilience in the scientific literature call for solutions as multifaceted and complex as the water system itself (Wong and Brown, 2009, Kennedy et al. 2012, Ashley et al 2003, 2005). As Kennedy et al. write: “Building resilience is not simply an engineering problem involving more dams and canals. It is a socioeconomic phenomenon that requires a highly interdisciplinary approach, including analysis of governance and social systems, as well as hydrology.” (Kennedy et al. 2012). In this direction, access to a diversity of water resources, including centralised and decentralised sources, is argued by Wong and Brown to be a resilient approach for water sensitive cities (Wong and Brown, 2009) and, in a similar vein, the urban harvest approach, which taps into both primary and secondary water resources at a local level, has proved effective in both the Netherlands and Australia as an aid for sustainable urban resource planning (Agudelo-Vera et al 2012).</p>
<p>Kennedy et al. also suggest thinking across geographical boundaries in terms of resource management. Novel technological approaches can provide greater efficiency in the allocation of scarce resources (Anzaldi, 2014, Helbing et al., 2012) and quick response to threats such as flooding (Young-Il and Kim, 2015) and water quality measurements (Shin et al., 2009). Yet, the strategies by which these technological advances are leveraged must be carefully chosen as there is a risk that the “smart city” paradigm will be pushed forward not for the purposes of resource efficiency, but rather for promotion of consumption of digital goods, resulting in ineffective interventions in resource use obfuscating an actual lessening or absence of effect on resilience (Viitanen and Kingston, 2014)</p>
<p>In terms of governance and social systems, Ostrom has shown that collective governance of resources, including water resources, has success on a local scale (Ostrom, 1990). Here, the advent of big data can be of use in facilitating a more integrated approach to governance by leveraging social interest. Open data and citizen science approaches can augment water treatment and provision services (Buckingham Shum et al.), and lessons from disaster response in Kathmandu suggest that local open data ecosystems can aide rapid response to events (Soden et al., 2014).</p>
<p>References</p>
<p>Agudelo-Vera C., Mels A., Keesman K., and Rijnaarts H.. 2012. The Urban Harvest Approach as an Aid for Sustainable Urban Resource Planning, Journal of Industrial Ecology, Volume 16, Issue 6, 839–850</p>
<p>Ashley, R. M., Balmforth, D. J., Saul, A. J. &amp; Blanksby, J. R. 2005 Flooding in the future. Water Sci. Technol. 52(5), 265–274.</p>
<p>Ashley, R. M., Blackwood, D. J., Butler, D., Davies, J. A., Jowitt, P. &amp; Smith, H. 2003 Sustainable decision making for the UK water industry. Eng. Sustainability 156(ES1), 41–49.</p>
<p>Buckingham Shum, S.; Aberer, K.; Schmidt, A.; Bishop, S.; Lukowicz, P.; Anderson, S.; Charalabidis, Y.; Domingue, D.; de Freitas, S.; Dunwell, I.; Edmonds, B.; Grey, F.; Haklay, M.; Jelasity, M.; Karpiˇstˇsenko, A.; Kohlhammer, J.; Lewis, J.; Pitt, J.; Sumner, R. and Helbing, D. (2012). Towards a global participatory platform: democratising open data, complexity science and collective intelligence. European Physical Journal Special Topics, 214(1), pp. 109–152.</p>
<p>Garmestani, Ahjond S.; Allen, Craig R.; Arnold, Craig Anthony (Tony); and Gunderson, Lance H., “Introduction: Social-Ecological Resilience and Law” (2014). Nebraska Cooperative Fish &amp; Wildlife Research Unit – Staff Publications. Paper 142. http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/ncfwrustaff/142</p>
<p>Haimes, Y.Y. On the Definition of Resilience in Systems, Risk Analysis, Vol. 29, No. 4, 2009, 498-501</p>
<p>Helbing D., S. Bishop, R. Conte, P. Lukowicz, and J.B. McCarthy, FuturICT: Participatory computing to understand and manage our complex world in a more sustainable and resilient way, Eur. Phys. J. Special Topics 214, 11–39 (2012)</p>
<p>Kennedy C., Baker L., Dhakal S., Ramaswami A., Sustainable Urban Systems, Journal of Industrial Ecology, 16, 6, 2012, 775-779</p>
<p>Matthews J.C., Disaster Resilience of Critical Water Infrastructure Systems, Journal of Structural Engineering, C6015001, DOI: 10.1061/(ASCE)ST.1943-541X.0001341 ,</p>
<p>Ohlsson, L, Water conflicts and social resource scarcity, Physics and Chemistry of the Earth, Part B: Hydrology, Oceans and Atmosphere, Volume 25, Issue 3, 2000, 213–220</p>
<p>Ostrom E., Governing the Commons (CUP, 1990) Schyns J.F., Hoekstra A.Y., Boolj M.J., Review and classification of indicators of green water availability and scarcity, Hydrology and Earth Systems Sciences Discources, 12, 5519-5594, 2015</p>
<p>Shin, P., Song, Y., Choi, Y., and Park, Y. (2009) Seoul (Korea) Online Water Quality Monitoring of Drinking Water. World Environmental and Water Resources Congress 2009: pp. 1-9.</p>
<p>Soden R., Budhathoki N., Palen L. Resilience-Building and the Crisis Informatics Agenda: Lessons Learned from Open Cities Kathmandu, Proceedings of the 11th International ISCRAM Conference, 339-348, 2014 g Viitanen J. and Kingston R., 2014 Environ Plan A, April 2014 vol. 46 no. 4 803-819</p>
<p>Young-Il and Kim, 2015 http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2015EGUGA..17.8193M</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.org/news/2015-12-01-recommendations-water-sector-open-data-citizen-stewardship.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Countdown 2030 - Citizen Science Challenges and Opportunities</title>
    <link>https://iilab.org/news/2015-11-30-countdown-2030.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Citizen science is a pretty wonderful phenomenon that is changing the dynamics of knowledge generation in the same way that open access is changing the dynamics of knowledge ownership. So how can we make it even better?</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The next step in citizen science is to incorporate different aspects of design - particularly ideas around embodied cognition, social development theory and human centric design. Why? Because the next step in the citizen science journey is to anchor it more fully in lived experience, to help citizen science and its enabling technology to create bridges between people and a lens through which to understand the world’s complexity.</p>
<p>I expand on these ideas in this talk, which was presented remotely at <a href="http://www.igp.ucl.ac.uk/igp-events-pub/countdown-2030">UCL’s Institute of Global Prosperity’s Countdown 2030 conference</a> on Saturday. The conference had an amazing line-up, looking at the advances being brought by young researchers that could have a significant impact on the development of science and society in the next 15 years. It was an honour to be part of the line-up organised by <a href="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/excites/people/academic-staff/muki-haklay">Muki Haklay of UCL ExCITES</a>.</p>
<p>Here’s the video of the recorded presentation:</p>
<center>
<div class="iframeWrapper">
<div class="video-container post-media">
<iframe src="//player.vimeo.com/video/147366069?color=506a85" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
<p>
<a href="http://vimeo.com/147366069">Countdown 2030 - Citizen Science Challenges and Opportunities</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/iilab">iilab</a> on <a href="https://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a>.
</p>
</div>
</div>
</center>
<p><br></p>
<p>And here are the slides with the transcript below, including some references:</p>
<center>
<div class="iframeWrapper">
<iframe src="//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/55640817" width="100%" height="600" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
<div style="margin-bottom:5px">
<strong> <a href="//www.slideshare.net/KatAusten/countdown2030-kat-austen" title="Countdown 2030 - Kat Austen" target="_blank">Countdown 2030 - Kat Austen</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="//www.slideshare.net/katausten" target="_blank">Kat Austen</a></strong>
</div>
</div>
</center>
<p><br></p>
<p>I want to talk about 2 aspects that I think could prove fruitful for citizen science now and in the future, namely creating a richer experience of data, and human-centered design. I’ll then open it up to more creative thoughts about the role of citizen science in our future society.</p>
<ul>
<li>Data can be misleading, and datasets need to be richer to help provide context.</li>
<li>Squashing a rich dataset into one node or line can lead to loss of information or misrepresentation</li>
<li>It’s also the case that diifferent modes of interaction with the data can produce different insights and behaviours. We understand the world - and data - in part from our physical interactions, and that aspect is something that’s is largely neglected.</li>
</ul>
<p><br></p>
<ul>
<li>We already know that the use of devices change how we think whether that’s in terms of spatial awareness, reasoning or interpretation</li>
<li>And we know that interacting with data through other senses uncovers different patterns in the data than visualisation - eg Brain Stethoscope by Parvisi and Chafe sonified EEG patterns as a more effective way to detect epileptic fits Epilepsy and Behaviour May 2015, Volume 46, Pages 53–54</li>
<li>We also make meaning of data through a cultural filter, so working with community interpretation of data also produces different insights and behaviours - something leveraged in citizen and DIY science.</li>
</ul>
<p>There are presently challenges in citizen science in terms of durability of projects - that is sustained engagement. A common question raised is also around the data quality - either from too few participants, from incomplete or sparse datasets, or poor adherence to scientific methodologies.</p>
<p>Finally, there are ethical and political considerations - in the worst case, citizen scientists can be viewed as unpaid data collectors, or in the case of gamified engagement as human ginuea pigs. Should citizens have more influence over citizen science projects than just funding them with taxes and contributing to them with their time? There’s also the possibility of missing out on the potential of innovation either in method or instrumentation, if citizen scientists are not fully engaged.</p>
<p>So, how do we make the most of citizen science projects for global prosperity? To do this we need to anchor citizen science in human experience, which should create greater understanding and more durable engagement.</p>
<p>I’m interested in using interdisciplinary methods to move into an even more human centred and holistic view of citizen science in a person’s life and in society. That translates into combining citizen science methods, with embodied experiences that put that our shared learning into context</p>
<p>Let me give you 2 examples of this in my work. One is from Piksel Festival in Bergen, Norway, and uses embodied cognition principles to create stronger relationships between citizens and the meaning of the data they produce in the course of their experiments.</p>
<p>With my collaborators, we’ve been working on developing tools to help anyone test for micro-plastics using household chemicals and equipment. We were also making and using DIY hydrophones to check for human-made sound pollution in the fjord.</p>
<p>From there we’ve also been working on informing a new way to engage with the data through design of a “coral empathy” prototype, which will eventually use the audio data captured by hydrophones to create and tune vibrations in a helmet. The microplastic pollution is translated into smells, which will be dialled up or down depending on the pollution that is detected.</p>
<p>My second example comes from my work at iilab, where we are working on centring first on the needs of the community and determining what data needs to be collected. In collaboration with UCL and Newcastle University’s Open Lab, we have recently launched the Engineering Comes Home project, where we’re investigating the use of community co-design methods in application to infrastructure engineering at the nexus of food, water, waste and energy resource use.</p>
<p>What data should be gathered is very open because there’s virtually no data around domestic and community behaviour around this nexus. We can let the community decide which indicators to focus on, hoping this will make the engagement sustainable, and to help the community engage with the politics of infrastructure.</p>
<p>In this project we will combine approaches from multiple disciplines alongside the knowledge from the community to understand and design for citizen sensing and intervention requirements.</p>
<p>Particularly pertinent for this project is the importance of creating a way to engage with the complexity of the interconnected food, waste, water and energy infrastructure systems, by designing prototype technologies that allow communities to connect with and intervene in these systems in a holistic way.</p>
<p>During the course of the project, it’s fundamental to create real links between people through the engagement with citizen science tools and data platforms. Here we can learn from work from community building with digital media - such as community forums and digital storytelling, and advances using tangible user interfaces for collaborative learning.</p>
<p>In 15 years, innovations from academia and hackerspaces alike will enable a more physical and emotive engagement with data gathering, processing and representation. This will make us more connected with our environment and will make complex systems easier to understand.</p>
<p>Science will be more integrated with society and politics, and both science and politics will be more participative. And people will feel more active and influential in the world they live in.</p>
<p>This more physical engagement with knowledge will create links between people, bringing people out of their data bubble. We will move beyond screens, beyond data, to a more integrated understanding and embodied experience of our knowledge - together.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.org/news/2015-11-30-countdown-2030.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Help us make a new tool to guide network mappers</title>
    <link>https://iilab.org/news/2015-08-14-toolbox-network-mapping.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>We are surrounded by complex systems and power structures, not least of which are the networks of links between people by which they change and are changed. Understanding these links can sometimes have important consequences - for instance if you see that a policy-maker has strong personal ties to a lobbying organisation, you may see their decisions in a different light.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>Mapping these social networks of influence can be an important tool for researchers, journalists, activists and others. There are many tools and methods out there aiming to do just this, and for the last few months we’ve been actively engaging with the <a href="http://influencemapping.org">Influence Mappers</a> community, who are working to create standards and resources that help those trying to document relationships between people, organisations, and political processes.</p>
<h2 id="the-influence-mapping-toolbox">The Influence Mapping Toolbox</h2>
<p>Over the next few months, iilab will be working on developing the <a href="http://influencemapping.org/influence-mapping-toolbox/">Influence Mapping Toolbox</a>, which will help newcomers (and more experienced people too) get started, learn and achieve their influence mapping goals.</p>
<p>It will provide information about inspiring projects, as well as the different methods and tools available for different teams and goals. We will build it using a human centered approach and will make our results available as we progress.</p>
<p>Our team will be made up of Kat (me), Head of Research and Design, Lilas, Research Associate, and Jun.</p>
<h2 id="we-need-you">We need you!</h2>
<p>We want to hear from both the experienced influence mapping community and with people just starting out. Your feedback will help us better design the Influence Mapping Toolbox.</p>
<p>Just starting a project? Recently developed one or a few projects? <strong>We’d like to invite you to <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/149mqSqwxCWZDkBT2RhEph-H4ZyOudcWjhbi2Wffz0vU/viewform">answer our questionnaire</a></strong>.</p>
<p>It will only take 10 minutes of your time and will help a lot to build the toolbox. You also can get in touch directly via email to influencemapping@iilab.org or by following the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/influencemapping">Influence Mapping Google Group</a> thread.</p>
<p>From <strong>experienced practitioners</strong>, we’d particularly like to hear about:</p>
<ul>
<li>Thinking back to when you first started on your influence mapping project, what were the questions you had and what type of resource would you have wanted as a guide?</li>
<li>Do you know anyone who’s just getting started on an influence mapping project?</li>
</ul>
<p>For more information about our process, please check out the community’s <a href="http://influencemapping.org/influence-mapping-toolbox/">Influence Mapping Toolbox</a> announcement, or get in touch to have a chat at <script type="text/javascript">
<!--
h='&#x69;&#x69;&#108;&#x61;&#98;&#46;&#x6f;&#114;&#x67;';a='&#64;';n='&#x69;&#110;&#102;&#108;&#x75;&#x65;&#110;&#x63;&#x65;&#x6d;&#x61;&#112;&#112;&#x69;&#110;&#x67;';e=n+a+h;
document.write('<a h'+'ref'+'="ma'+'ilto'+':'+e+'" clas'+'s="em' + 'ail">'+e+'<\/'+'a'+'>');
// -->
</script><noscript>&#x69;&#110;&#102;&#108;&#x75;&#x65;&#110;&#x63;&#x65;&#x6d;&#x61;&#112;&#112;&#x69;&#110;&#x67;&#32;&#x61;&#116;&#32;&#x69;&#x69;&#108;&#x61;&#98;&#32;&#100;&#x6f;&#116;&#32;&#x6f;&#114;&#x67;</noscript>.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.org/news/2015-08-14-toolbox-network-mapping.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>How do we make UK water provision more resilient?</title>
    <link>https://iilab.org/news/2015-07-28-uk-water-resilience.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Open call for consultation from UK water regulator Ofwat as part of Kat’s work with the resilience working group</p>
<!--more-->
<p>As cultures we constantly evolve in our approach to different issues. In terms of human existence within our environment, we have transitioned from living embedded in and at the mercy of it, through processes of industrialisation, to environmentalism, and sustainability - and now we have now reached a concept of resilience that is prominent even at a policy level.</p>
<h2 id="the-ofwat-water-resilience-task-and-finish-group">The OFWAT Water Resilience Task and Finish Group</h2>
<p>In the UK this takes shape at government level in the form of directives that aim to improve resilience accross the country and in different sectors. This includes, among others, <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/collections/sector-resilience-plans">sector resilience plans</a>, <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/emergency-planning">emergency planning</a> and risk assessment, <a href="https://www.gov.uk/resilience-in-society-infrastructure-communities-and-businesses">engagement with society</a>, and - in terms of water - the <a href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2014/21/contents/enacted">Water Act 2014</a>, which includes a <a href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2014/21/part/1/chapter/3/crossheading/general-duties-of-the-water-services-regulation-authority/enacted">duty for the UK water regulator to secure resilience in the water sector</a>.</p>
<p>To understand how to fulfil this duty, the UK water regulator, <a href="http://ofwat.gov.uk">Ofwat</a>, convened at the start of 2015 the <a href="http://www.ofwat.gov.uk/regulating/tools/prs_web20150706resiliencetaskandfinish">Water Resilience Task and Finish Group</a>, chaired by <a href="http://www.waterwise.org.uk/pages/jacob-tompkins.html">Jacob Tompkins</a>, MD of <a href="http://www.waterwise.org.uk">Waterwise</a>. Jacob approached me to participate as a member of the group, alongside colleagues from within the water industry, academia and environmental organisations.</p>
<p>I am thrilled and humbled to be helping provide recommendations that may shape the UK’s approach to water resilience. With the group, I am working on two areas: a broad look at what water resilience looks like from a multitude of perspectives, which Jun and I are now turning into a map of water resilience with the aim of producing a systems map that can be used by policy makers and stakeholders alike to understand leverage points in which they could have agency to bring about a more resilient approach to water; and a body of research on community based water resilience strategies.</p>
<h2 id="working-towards-a-clear-definition-of-resilience">Working towards a clear definition of Resilience</h2>
<p>Defining resilience is almost a specialisation in itself, and no definition will please all the people all the time. But part of the workgroup’s aim is to come up with a workable definition that focusses on water resilience in the UK. Our work has already had an impact in shaping <a href="http://www.ofwat.gov.uk/regulating/tools/pap_con20150708resilence.pdf?download=Download">Ofwat’s definition of resilience in their resilience consultation,</a> which is taking place alongside our independent work.</p>
<p>The definition so far is:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Resilience is the ability to cope with, and recover from, disruption, trends and variability in order to maintain services for people and protect the natural environment, now and in the future.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><br></p>
<p>Being part of the working group is a valuable two way learning experience. With a perspective from outside the water sector, it’s been interesting for me to learn more about the national-scale processes in play. It’s also been interesting to see how community and citizens are perceived differently by different stakeholders in the discussion - for water companies the agency of a customer is predominantly through their ability or willingness to pay, whereas from my perspective - something that chimes with our work at iilab and Open Droplet - these customers are citizens with agency that can be acted in multiple ways either individually or as part of a community. This may take the form of engaging with their political representatives, their water company, as a community member working with organisations to prevent flooding or improve river water quality, or by taking steps to decentralise or create multiple modes for their water supply.</p>
<h2 id="unpacking-perspectives-on-resilience">Unpacking perspectives on Resilience</h2>
<p>Another interesting difference was how each of us perceived the “final point” at which water resilience is felt. It became clear through our discussions that for most of the members from the water sector, water resilience came from the continued functioning of the current water sector infrastructure, facilitated by the extant water companies. For me, however, water resilience comes down to people having access to appropriately clean water and waste water treatment, however that comes about, and resilience of ecological systems (including human nodes) to water changes such as flooding, changing salination, and so on. I’ve endeavoured to bring these different viewpoints to the working group meetings and to my work mapping and researching for the final report.</p>
<p>Here comes the fun bit, though. The approach of the working group is participative. At iilab, we will be sharing both the water map and the research when it’s in a more complete state. To help inform both the mapping, the research, and the recommendations for Ofwat, the group has generated a survey for interested parties who might have knowledge or ideas to share with respect to working towards water resilience.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-contribute">How to contribute</h2>
<p>What do you think about water resilience? I’d like to share the survey with you - here’s the agreed wording for doing that:</p>
<p>“The UK Water Resilience Task Force would like your views, please complete this short survey, ideally by mid-August”</p>
<p>Contribute to the work by <a href="https://cranfielduniversity.eu.qualtrics.com/SE/?SID=SV_8BbfGUtYjIfeV6Z">completing the survey, hosted by Cranfield University</a>.</p>
<p>I’m informed that the data policy for the survey is that the anonymised data will be made open source unless individuals make a compelling request to be excluded from that.</p>
<p>And if you’re interested to, you can follow or join the UK Water Resilience <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/groups/UK-Water-Resilience-8310265/about">LinkedIn G</a>roup. You can also email at <script type="text/javascript">
<!--
h='&#x6f;&#102;&#x77;&#x61;&#116;&#46;&#x67;&#x73;&#x69;&#46;&#x67;&#x6f;&#118;&#46;&#x75;&#x6b;';a='&#64;';n='&#114;&#x65;&#x73;&#x69;&#108;&#x69;&#x65;&#110;&#x63;&#x65;&#x63;&#x6f;&#110;&#x73;&#x75;&#108;&#116;&#x61;&#116;&#x69;&#x6f;&#110;';e=n+a+h;
document.write('<a h'+'ref'+'="ma'+'ilto'+':'+e+'" clas'+'s="em' + 'ail">'+e+'<\/'+'a'+'>');
// -->
</script><noscript>&#114;&#x65;&#x73;&#x69;&#108;&#x69;&#x65;&#110;&#x63;&#x65;&#x63;&#x6f;&#110;&#x73;&#x75;&#108;&#116;&#x61;&#116;&#x69;&#x6f;&#110;&#32;&#x61;&#116;&#32;&#x6f;&#102;&#x77;&#x61;&#116;&#32;&#100;&#x6f;&#116;&#32;&#x67;&#x73;&#x69;&#32;&#100;&#x6f;&#116;&#32;&#x67;&#x6f;&#118;&#32;&#100;&#x6f;&#116;&#32;&#x75;&#x6b;</noscript> and join in on Twitter using #resilience.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.org/news/2015-07-28-uk-water-resilience.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Supporting decisions in a complex world</title>
    <link>https://iilab.org/news/2015-01-30-decisions-complex-world.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>As Adam Bly identified in 2012 at Ars Electronica: The Big Picture, complexity is the challenge of our time and what we need is an image that captures it. We think it is critical to develop the tools that will help reduce this complexity to its essentials, and make it easier to understand and more accessible. That way, we can face some of our time’s difficult challenges armed with the best information we can get.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>At the edge of the scientific inquiry into how policy decisions are made, iilab’s Head of Research and Design, Kat Austen, as part of her consultancy work, is involved in reviewing the European Commission’s DG Connect GSS Cluster projects. She recently <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/en/news/report-meeting-projects-funded-global-systems-science-gss">reported on a meeting of projects funded in Global Systems Science (GSS) that look at evidence-based policy making</a>. It prompted us to think about how understanding and visualising - in the broadest sense of the word - complex systems can help in supporting vital decisions from the individual to the international level.</p>
<h2 id="revealing-complex-networks">Revealing Complex Networks</h2>
<p>One of the most important challenges facing our times is climate change, and one of the reasons it’s so challenging is because it requires us to have an understanding of our influence within a complex network that is bigger in both space and time than our human experience. Nevertheless, combatting it requires decision-making on every level. GSS’s INSITE project looks at the “importance of narrative to society and individuals both in its emergence and its effect” and questions the assumptions behind our models and how much norms influence our ways of thinking about problems. These considerations inform our community based approaches for <a href="https://iilab.org/projects/open-droplet.html">Open Droplet</a>, our open source, open hardware water measurement sensor that will be networked, easy to use and allows people and communities to steward their water use.</p>
<p>In our research and design, we are paying particular attention to cultural attitudes towards water and how it affects consumption of resources. We’ll post here later the results of a 5 city overview undertaken for iilab by UCL Masters students which includes cultural analysis in addition infrastructure and technology analysis. When it comes to stewardship of natural resources, evolving cultural attitudes goes beyond current techniques to prompt behavior change, such as neighbor competition or financial incentives, and is something that we are researching to shape the data interfaces we’re developing for Open Droplet - what ways might there be of hinting at our influence in complex networks, without having to show them explicitly?</p>
<p>Sometimes, you do want to see these networks explicitly. We have also recently joined the <a href="https://influencemapping.org/">Influence Mapping</a> group, which looks at data-driven social network analysis projects to understand influence relationships between people and organisations. It will also map out the network of policy-makers involved in international trade negotiations around the regulation of intellectual property.</p>
<h2 id="gathering-evidence-from-open-sources">Gathering evidence from open sources</h2>
<p>But how do we find out about these networks? Beyond the work that aims to collect evidence about domestic water consumption with Open Droplet, iilab participates in projects where technology is used to improve the collection, analysis and presentation of evidence in ways that involve the public and informs policy making, such as the <a href="/project/open-integrity.html">Open Integrity Index</a>, ECSA (also with DG Connect), the <a href="/project/open-oil.html">Open Oil corporate navigator</a>.</p>
<p>The text mining and semantic analysis tools developed by the GSS Cluster - for instance the tools used in GLODERS for analysing open source court and police documents - are relevant to our work in facilitating the sourcing of structured evidence by scraping open source documents. When we participated in the Open Oil hackathon in Berlin in January, we explored a number of methods by which to extract this information. For instance, ContentMine has developed new technology which can be used to extract diagrams from PDFs and might be of use to mine information about company organograms. Also Open Oil is now partnering with CrowdCrafting to <a href="http://crowdcrafting.org/app/openoil/">crowdsource the analysis of contracts from the oil industry</a>.</p>
<p>In the <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/digital-agenda/en/news/no-disconnect-strategy-workshop-european-capability-situational">ECSA project</a> we also look at how “to augment EU decision-making capabilities with reliable and real-time or almost real-time information concerning human rights violations and/or restrictions of fundamental freedoms in connection with the digital environment.” As part of the study we are looking at the feasibility of collecting and analysing information from open sources including internet measurement infrastructure and publicly available reports about potential human rights violation incidents.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-trust-the-evidence">How to trust the evidence?</h2>
<p>As we’re all aware, not all information online is trustworthy, and as a society we are always navigating who to listen to and what to believe in an era of information overload. The EU Community project aims to address trust and reliability by assigning authority to people and documents. Open Integrity Index, on the other hand, looks into trustworthiness by collecting evidence from the crowd and experts about the practices adopted by tool developers with regards to security and privacy. When submitting evidence it must be accompanied by a link which makes it verifiable by anyone. While there are still challenges around assigning authority to people, particularly when dealing with complex and multi-faceted issues like digital security and privacy, this transparency and breaking down problems into smaller parts help focus the debate and make the analysis more robust and legible.</p>
<p>We used this same approach with the <a href="http://newsverify.atchai.com/">News Verify project</a>, in collaboration with Atchai, where we developed a news publishing platform with a verification framework. NewsVerify allows journalists to curate pieces of evidence from social media and the web, and tie them together as news with a verification status and narrative that can be seen by readers and updated as more evidence is added. Checkdesk from Meedan is further innovating in this domain by developing a liveblogging tool for journalists, with built-in tools to allow citizen journalists and staff journalists alike to make and verify reports. These novel approaches in journalism help open up the way to informed citizen participation in policy making.</p>
<h2 id="modelling-and-data-analysis">Modelling and Data Analysis</h2>
<p>The tools we need to build to address challenges in evidence based decision making should be sophisticated enough to capture the essential complexity of reality, but succeed in being in simple and accessible to their audience and users. Computer science has a lot of room for development to get rid of the non-essential complexity which plagues existing large software systems (cf <a href="https://github.com/papers-we-love/papers-we-love/blob/master/design/out-of-the-tar-pit.pdf">Out of the tar pit, B. Moseley &amp; P. Marks 2006</a>). In turn, there are exciting design challenges in making more simple to develop these sophisticated tools in more robust ways, as well as in creating simple, accessible, usable - and in some cases emotive - interfaces with data, and bridging the gap between the digital and corporeal worlds. This can only be the result of a multi-disciplinary effort that is firmly grounded in technological and social innovation.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.org/news/2015-01-30-decisions-complex-world.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Nix + OSX + HaskellNG = Dependency Paradise ?</title>
    <link>https://iilab.org/news/2015-03-27-nix-osx-haskellng-hakyll.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’ve recently started to learn Haskell and have been in the books for a few months, so didn’t yet have to experience the practical side of what comes with the workflow of working with Haskell.</p>
<p>I decided to try getting my hands dirty with a simple project, migrating the iilab website to the Haskell static site generator <a href="http://jaspervdj.be/hakyll/">Hakyll</a>. In this post I look at how I setup my development environment, and hope to ease the pain for others that are used to the simple <code>npm install</code> style workflows by looking at the latest in how to deal with Haskell dependency problems also known as “cabal hell”.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>Last year after a difficult experience with Jekyll for the Amnesty International Panic Button website, I looked around other approaches to do static website generation and, given I was into JS at the time and like the small modules approach, I settled on metalsmith, which seemed to have a clever design, based on a configurable pipeline, that seemed flexible enough. When I installed it, I did have to hack a few modules to make them do what I wanted, but it seemed straighforward enough. More recently I wanted to do a bit of freshening up on our website, and was looking at building a workflow with css/js concatenation and minimisation. Given how metalsmith was supposed to be this versatile, build pipeline, I thought it would be simple but I got turned off by the lack of clarity, and things started breaking pretty badly when I tried to upgrade modules to latest versions.</p>
<p>That’s when, in a familiar sequence of events, <a href="http://chriswarbo.net/blog/2014-07-14-nixos.html">well captured</a> as</p>
<ul>
<li>Try to do something simple</li>
<li>Fail</li>
<li>Go down a rabbit hole in an attempt to fix it</li>
</ul>
<p>I recursed through a few rabbit holes after my metalsmith/npm woes by trying Hakyll, running into cabal hell, decided to try Nix, saw that it was a bit bleeding edge for OSX, managed to go through that more or less, until I bumped into a compilation problem with the haskellPackages and was helped by the nice folks on the <code>##nix-darwin</code> IRC channel and pointed to the even more bleeding edge HaskellNG Nix approach which of course, is how deep the rabbit hole goes.</p>
<p>In short, here’s how the pieces fit together:</p>
<ul>
<li>Nix provides <strong>declarative</strong> and <strong>deterministic</strong> package management. Read about <a href="https://www.domenkozar.com/2014/03/11/why-puppet-chef-ansible-arent-good-enough-and-we-can-do-better/">why you should care</a>. <br><br></li>
<li><p>HaskellNG draws on Nix to make Haskell package management <strong>declarative</strong> and goes beyond the current <code>cabal sandbox</code> approach by allowing:</p>
<ul>
<li>reuse of already compiled binaries (instead of having to recompile separately in every sandbox) and</li>
<li>dealing with dependencies at the compiler (and cabal) level, therefore <a href="https://mail.haskell.org/pipermail/haskell-cafe/2015-March/118817.html">allowing to test bleeding edge compiler features</a> without fear of messing up your development environment.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="nix">Nix</h2>
<p>Nix is a package manager which is also the foundation of a linux distribution called NixOS which uses the philosophy of Nix through and through to provide a well regarded linux distribution. What Nix offers is a reliable way to manage dependencies and escape the various type of hells that the problem creates (DLL hell, cabal hell, the type of spagetthi that systems folk don’t want…). It does this by knowing the complete dependency tree of all the packages it manages. This reminds me of docker’s declarative approach to system configuratio, except that I think that docker’s layered approach at the file system level brings an interesting lower level dimension. In any case, with Nix, several binaries with a different set of dependencies can coexist on your system, and more importantly, use the functional immutable approach to Nix package dependencies in order to keep your environment and yourself health, sane and functional.</p>
<p>A few things that Nix does is make sure dependencies are exact (by using binary hashes in a clever way - which includes all the dependency tree of the binary) and only reuse them when necessary. This means that the nix store holds a range of binary images which might be used by different other binaries and can coexist happily.</p>
<p>Nix then offers a number of wrapping tools to make these binaries available, for instance, when installing with <code>nix-env -iA nixpkgs.somePackage</code> you’re installing somePackage inside your <strong>user environment</strong> which is in fact symbolic links to the nix store defined in your <code>~/.nix-profile</code> directory.</p>
<p>When using <code>nix-shell</code> you’re using a <strong>project environment</strong> which might have different dependencies.</p>
<h2 id="nix-on-osx">Nix on OSX</h2>
<p>The great thing, given my current dependency on this fruity old laptop and its pretty UX, is that Nix is available on OSX. I took me a little bit of meandering to find out because there are <a href="http://www.chrisjr.org/posts/2014/12/22/nix-osx-haskell/">outdated blog posts</a> on the web (which give workarounds from <strong>before</strong> the OSX changes were marged into the Nix master branch) that <a href="https://nixos.org/wiki/Nix_on_OS_X#Using_Nix_on_10.9_and_10.10">these instructions on the NixOS Wiki about <strong>Using Nix on 10.9 and 10.10</strong></a> actually work just fine. I did bump into a problem because I started installing from the wrong git repo, a number of weird errors came up after switching to the correct instructions which meant that I had to restart from scratch and remove all the nix directories (/nix/store and ˜/.nix-profile).</p>
<h2 id="haskellng-on-nix">HaskellNG on Nix</h2>
<p>When I first bumped into <a href="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.distributions.nixos/15513">this post about the new way</a> to do Haskell with Nix, I thought : “Oh, this looks great but very bleeding edge and I’m down several rabbit holes already so let’s look at it later”. So I went my merry way installing following <a href="https://nixos.org/wiki/Haskell">the official Nix instructions on the wiki</a>. But then after installing the Haskell toolkit (apparently the <a href="https://www.mail-archive.com/nix-dev@lists.science.uu.nl/msg13622.html">Nix crowd is too cool for the Haskell Platform</a>) I found out that the Nix tribe on OSX seemed to have already left the old ways behind and migrated to HaskellNG. I found out because I ran into this error:</p>
<pre><code>installing ‘haskell-hakyll-ghc7.8.4-4.6.1.1-shared’
error: Package ‘util-linux-2.26’ in ‘/../dev/nixpkgs/pkgs/os-specific/linux/util-linux/default.nix:54’ is not supported on ‘x86_64-darwin’, refusing to evaluate.</code></pre>
<p>Here are a few reasons why HaskellNG is the way to go, as summarised in the <a href="http://lists.science.uu.nl/pipermail/nix-dev/2015-January/015591.html">[Nix-dev] A Journey into the Haskell NG infrastructure: Part I</a> post:</p>
<ul>
<li>The NG package set contains the latest version of every package available from Hackage</li>
<li>Haskell NG supports GHC 7.10.x.</li>
<li>Haskell NG allows you to configure the hell out of your installation.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="step-by-step">Step by step</h2>
<p>To recap, here’s what it took to set things up: - following <a href="https://nixos.org/wiki/Nix_on_OS_X#Using_Nix_on_10.9_and_10.10">these steps to install Nix on OSX 10.10</a> - adapting <a href="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.distributions.nixos/15035/focus=15161">these steps</a> to haskellng - and <a href="http://wiki.ocharles.org.uk/Nix">this description of the haskell cabal workflow</a>.</p>
<h3 id="install-nix-on-osx">Install Nix on OSX</h3>
<p>A <a href="https://nixos.org/wiki/Nix_on_OS_X#Using_Nix_on_10.9_and_10.10">slightly more concise version of the official Nix wiki instructions</a>. ** I’d recommend heading over there for the latest!!! **</p>
<p>First, make sure to install Xcode or Command Line Tools (or both).</p>
<pre><code>$ curl https://nixos.org/nix/install | sh
$ . $HOME/.nix-profile/etc/profile.d/nix.sh
$ git clone https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs.git
$ nix-channel --remove nixpkgs
$ cd ~/.nix-defexpr
$ rm -rf *
$ ln -s /path/of/nixpkgs/clone nixpkgs</code></pre>
<pre><code>$ sudo mkdir /etc/nix</code></pre>
<p>Create a <code>/etc/nix/nix.conf</code> file with</p>
<pre><code>binary-caches = http://cache.nixos.org/ </code></pre>
<p>Update the .bashrc (change your USERNAME):</p>
<pre><code>export NIX_PATH=nixpkgs=/Users/USERNAME/dev/nixpkgs</code></pre>
<p>Source this</p>
<pre><code>$ source ~/.bashrc</code></pre>
<h3 id="configure-nix-for-haskell">Configure Nix for Haskell</h3>
<p>Create a ~/.nixpkgs directory and create a <code>~/.nixpkgs/config.nix</code> file which will be read each time you use nix</p>
<pre><code>{
  packageOverrides = super: let self = super.pkgs; in
  {
    haskellEnv = self.haskellngPackages.ghcWithPackages (p: with p; [
      cabal2nix
      cabal-install
    ]);
  };
}</code></pre>
<p>Install the haskellEnv with</p>
<pre><code>$ nix-env -iA nixpkgs.haskellEnv</code></pre>
<p>All of the other dependencies necessary for building your hakyll blog should be in the shell.nix generated by cabal2nix based on what is specified in the cabal file (where you would add/remove dependencies and rerun cabal2nix).</p>
<h3 id="create-a-nix-environment-for-your-project">Create a Nix environment for your project</h3>
<p>Go to the directory which contains the <code>.cabal</code> file of your haskell project and use <code>cabal2nix</code> to help create a <code>shell.nix</code> environment with the right dependencies.</p>
<pre><code>$ cabal2nix --shell . &gt; shell.nix</code></pre>
<p>When running this the first time I had an error about the nixpkgs directory and had to source ~/.bashrc with the proper $NIX_PATH variable.</p>
<pre><code>$ nix-shell --command &#39;cabal configure&#39;</code></pre>
<p>I got an error message about a nonfree license. Looking more into it, it’s my project that’s the culprit: the hakyll cabal package isn’t declaring a license. Wow, never got a build tool tell me that before. But I guess it makes a whole lot of sense, and it led me to <a href="https://github.com/haskell/cabal/issues/847#issuecomment-87065077">ponder about</a> what license a website generator should have, is it content or is it code?</p>
<p>I only spent a very short amount of time using cabal, and it seems that with the latest version and <code>cabal sandbox</code> things improved significantly. Cabal sandboxes allow several version of libraries to co-exist. But the time it took for spinning up a sandbox for a large project is quite long and in the worst case scenario, when dependencies reach into packages that are in the Haskell distribution (like cabal itself) then things start to be quite difficult. What Nix promises is that everything is separated by default, and when it’s safe to share packages (same hash of the whole dependency tree) then they won’t be rebuilt, meaning less compilation when its not needed! Nix still offers ways to control dependencies in a very granular way (what seems to be called deep overrides).</p>
<h3 id="build-your-project">Build your project</h3>
<p>Time to cabal build:</p>
<pre><code>$ cabal build</code></pre>
<p>Note that this should be doable from the user environment (i.e. without the nix-shell command) except that it fails with this error:</p>
<pre><code>ghc-7.8.4/include/Stg.h:65:10:
     fatal error: &#39;math.h&#39; file not found
#include &lt;math.h&gt;</code></pre>
<p>Oops, seems like <a href="https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs/issues/6390">this thread</a> says that things don’t quite work the way it’s supposed to on OSX (because of the clang compiler). The option seems to be to rebuild everything with <code>export NIX_CFLAGS_COMPILE=&quot;-idirafter /usr/include&quot;</code>.</p>
<p>Instead I give a shot to running cabal (therefore ghc) from within the nix-shell and tada, it works:</p>
<pre><code>$ nix-shell --command &#39;cabal build&#39;
Building iilab-org-hakyll-0.1.0.0...
Preprocessing executable &#39;site&#39; for iilab-org-hakyll-0.1.0.0...
[1 of 1] Compiling Main             ( site.hs, dist/build/site/site-tmp/Main.o)
Linking dist/build/site/site ...</code></pre>
<h2 id="the-workflow">The workflow</h2>
<p>So here it is, I created a simple <code>rebuild.sh</code> script to rebuild the Hakyll binary and run it with the <code>clean</code> and <code>watch</code> arguments:</p>
<pre><code>#!/bin/bash
set -e
nix-shell --command &#39;cabal build&#39;
./site clean
./site watch</code></pre>
<p>When needed I can also run the repl with</p>
<pre><code>$ nix-shell --command &#39;cabal repl&#39;</code></pre>
<p>If I add some Haskell imports and need to update the dependencies, I can do so in the cabal file and regenerate the shell.nix file with <code>cabal2nix --shell . &gt; shell.nix</code>.</p>
<h2 id="epilogue">Epilogue</h2>
<p>The tooling for Haskell development seems to be evolving fast and progressively making things easier for juggling with dependencies. However the reality is that it is still far from being as simple as other development environments and takes quite a lot of work to setup properly. I also realise that I’m a bit worried about trying to set that up again on another machine if I have to. I do think that the benefits definitely outweigh the drawbacks, and that investing the time to set this up will result in peace of mind when wanting to try out the bleeding edge of Haskell without worrying about breaking other projects because of dependencies. The folks on IRC were very helpful, especially Henry Till (<code>henrytill</code> on IRC) who helped review this post and I recommend heading to the <code>##nix-darwin</code> IRC Channel on freenode if you run into problems.</p>
<p>I’ll share more about why Haskell and Functional Programming matter, as well as my experience with using Hakyll and migrating from metalsmith in a next post but the iilab site is now generated with Hakyll and the <a href="https://github.com/iilab/iilab.org-hakyll">source code is of course available on github</a>.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.org/news/2015-03-27-nix-osx-haskellng-hakyll.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Panic Button @ Labtogether</title>
    <link>https://iilab.org/news/2015-01-15-betterplace-labtogether-video.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>In this video, Jun Matsushita addresses the role of the <strong>Open and Human Centered process</strong> that pervaded the <a href="/projects/panic-button.html">Panic Button</a> project since its start in 2011.</p>
<!--more-->
<p><br></p>
<center>
<div class="iframeWrapper">
<iframe width="100%" height="*" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/n6YS2Fq0hww?showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
</div>
</center>
<p><br></p>
<p>We’ve <a href="/news/2014-11-06-betterplace-labtogether.html">written about the presentation</a> of our work with <a href="http://amnesty.org/">Amnesty International</a> on the <a href="https://panicbutton.io">Panic Button app</a> at the <a href="http://www.betterplace-lab.org/labtogether">Lab Together 2014</a>. The Betterplace Lab is a research lab exploring digital innovations to help people, organizations and companies working in the social sector.</p>
<p>You can also <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/junjmatsushita/iilab-panic-button-betterplace">see the presentation on slideshare</a> which reviews the major phases of the project and presents some of the outcomes that iilab participated in realising.</p>
<center>
<div class="iframeWrapper">
<iframe src="//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/41613390" width="100%" height="600" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
<div style="margin-bottom:5px">
<strong> <a href="//www.slideshare.net/junjmatsushita/iilab-panic-button-betterplace" title="iilab - Panic button - betterplace" target="_blank">iilab - Panic button - betterplace</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="//www.slideshare.net/junjmatsushita" target="_blank">Jun Matsushita</a></strong>
</div>
</div>
</center>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.org/news/2015-01-15-betterplace-labtogether-video.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Open and Human Centric technology - Presenting Panic Button at Labtogether</title>
    <link>https://iilab.org/news/2014-11-06-betterplace-labtogether.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Betterplace Lab invited iilab to present our work with <a href="http://amnesty.org/">Amnesty International</a> on the <a href="https://panicbutton.io">Panic Button app</a> at the <a href="http://www.betterplace-lab.org/labtogether">Lab Together 2014</a>.</p>
<p>The main focus of my presentation was the role of the <strong>Open and Human Centered process</strong> that pervaded the project since it started in 2011.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The Betterplace Lab is a research lab exploring digital innovations to help people, organizations and companies working in the social sector. At the Lab Together this year, they held a discussion on digital privacy with our friends <a href="https://www.tacticaltech.org/">Tactical Technology Collective</a> and the new Data and Politics project lead Fieke Jansen, panels on Crowdfinancing and Productive failure, and presentations on digital relief trends.</p>
<iframe src="//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/41613390" width="100%" height="600" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
<div style="margin-bottom:5px">
<strong> <a href="//www.slideshare.net/junjmatsushita/iilab-panic-button-betterplace" title="iilab - Panic button - betterplace" target="_blank">iilab - Panic button - betterplace</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="//www.slideshare.net/junjmatsushita" target="_blank">Jun Matsushita</a></strong>
</div>
<p>Panic Button didn’t come fully formed out of the <a href="https://openideo.com/challenge/amnesty/realisation/">Open Ideo open innovation process</a>, that it took a lot of iterations in prototyping and later in implementation to get to <a href="https://panicbutton.io">where the application is today</a>.</p>
<p>Also, Open Source is an useful approach to improve the sustainability of a social impact project. It allowed iilab to pick up where Toughtworks had left, and will allow other developers to get onboard in the future. A question from the audience correctly pointed out that there are other factors to be able to support the <a href="http://oss-watch.ac.uk/resources/howtobuildcommunity">emergence of an open source community around a project</a> and Panic Button is still in an incubation phase with a few <a href="https://github.com/iilab/PanicButton/graphs/contributors">contributors</a> including paid ones.</p>
<p>Crucially we used an <a href="https://github.com/iilab/PanicButton-Design">Open Design approach</a> which included the use of <a href="https://github.com/iilab/PanicButton-Design/tree/master/Archive/5_Prototype_v2/Prototype%20v2%20Paper%20wireframes">paper based prototypes</a> and a <a href="https://github.com/iilab/PanicButton-Design/tree/master/Usability%20Testing">structured method to collect the results</a> of user testing. We gathered security experts, also with a human centric and <a href="https://tacticaltech.org/holistic-security">holistic security</a> approach to evaluate risks and feed into the <a href="https://github.com/iilab/PanicButton/blob/master/docs/SECURITY.md">security design and documentation</a> of Panic Button.</p>
<p>I wish there would have been more time for interaction with the audience, but the feedback on twitter was good so I hope the presentation provided some food for thought.</p>
<center>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en">
<p>
<a href="https://twitter.com/iilab"><span class="citation">@iilab</span></a> presents <a href="https://twitter.com/amnesty"><span class="citation">@amnesty</span></a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/panicbutton?src=hash">#panicbutton</a> app. Seems like model partnership &amp; process for this open source project. <a href="https://twitter.com/OpenStateBER"><span class="citation">@OpenStateBER</span></a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/labtogether?src=hash">#labtogether</a>
</p>
— Anja Adler (<span class="citation">@digitalnatural</span>) <a href="https://twitter.com/digitalnatural/status/530410525549924353">November 6, 2014</a>
</blockquote>
<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
</center>
<p>We’re hoping to share the video soon, but if you have any thoughts so far, please get in touch in the comments or <a href="https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=via+%40iilab+http%3A%2F%2Fbit.ly%2F11sHEgv+%23labtogether&amp;source=clicktotweet&amp;related=clicktotweet">with twitter</a> via <span class="citation">@iilab</span> #labtogether. <br> <br></p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2014 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.org/news/2014-11-06-betterplace-labtogether.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
