<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
    <channel>
        <title>iilab - Innovative Technology For Social Impact</title>
        <link>https://iilab.org</link>
        <description><![CDATA[iilab harnesses information innovation to help your social good initiatives improve their human impact.]]></description>
        <atom:link href="https://iilab.org/rss.xml" rel="self"
                   type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
    <title>Panic Button: Lessons for the Tech for Good Sector</title>
    <link>https://iilab.org/news/2017-09-03-panic-button-lessons-learned.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><em>This post is by <a href="https://twitter.com/TanyaOCarroll">Tanya O’Carroll</a>, Adviser Tech and Human Rights, Amnesty International; <a href="https://twitter.com/Ingleton">Danna Ingleton</a>, Adviser, Human Rights Defenders; and <a href="https://iilab.org/#team">Jun Matsushita</a>, Founder and CEO, iilab.</em></p>
<p>Making the <a href="/news/2017-09-02-panic-button-retiring-the-app.html">decision to cease support for the Panic Button app</a> was not an easy one, but it was also not an empty one. We believe that diving into the challenges we faced, and sharing them with our communities is key to building similar – and better – tools in the future. The challenges we faced are interlinked, and by no means specific merely to us.</p>
<!--more-->
<h2 id="the-short-lived-boom-in-apps-4-good">The short-lived boom in apps 4 good</h2>
<p>When we started this project in 2012, there was a lot of excitement about “tech 4 good.” Lots of organizations in the social change sector were seeking ways to innovate, and the sector was awash with small grants for technology projects.</p>
<p>However, if there is one theme of the last few years, it’s that there is still no functioning revenue model for funding sustainable and scalable technology in the social sector.</p>
<p>In 2012, the Ford Foundation provided Amnesty International with a grant of $125,000 to explore how we could use technology more directly in our work. With this, the organization hired a part-time post on tech and human rights, funded an <a href="https://challenges.openideo.com/challenge/amnesty/brief">open innovation challenge with OpenIDEO</a> and <a href="https://www.amnesty.org.uk/blogs/ether/how-turn-mobile-phone-alert-system-activists">built a first version</a> of the Panic Button app. We were able to build off this a year later with £100,000 from Google as <a href="https://www.amnesty.org.uk/blogs/ether/thank-you-our-mobile-panic-button-receives-%C2%A3100000">runners-up in the Global Impact Awards</a>. This grant funded the beta version of the app and a global pilot with more than 100 HRDs in Central America, East Africa and South-East Asia.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If there is one theme of the last few years, it’s that there is still no functioning revenue model for funding sustainable and scalable technology in the social sector.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We were convinced that once up and running, we would be able to demonstrate the concrete need for Panic Button, thereby attracting further long-term funding and permitting us to hire a project team. Our vision was to spin off Panic Button from Amnesty International, allowing us to explore a wider range of revenue models that would permit the app to scale, evolve and localize to cater to a greater number of countries and languages over time.</p>
<p>Unfortunately this never happened. Amnesty continued to put its own resources into keeping the project afloat but these were always small and temporary injections of resourcing. As such, the Panic Button project became a lesson in ‘what comes after innovation’. Despite broad community buy-in and a clear and stated need for the app by users, we couldn’t secure the funding that would move the project beyond its first, fledgling phase.</p>
<p>This has been a common experience of many technology projects over the last few years. Foundations have gotten cold feet when it comes to funding technology projects — and especially apps. One of the few funds that does provide sustained multi-year funding for technology projects is <a href="https://www.opentech.fund/">the Open Technology Fund (OTF)</a> —which has helped apps such as the end-to-end encrypted messaging service Signal make it to scale. But as OTF receives US State Department funding, it rules it out for organizations like Amnesty International who do not accept government funds.</p>
<h2 id="the-false-alert-problem">The false alert problem</h2>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/news/panic-button-false-alert-problem.png" />

</div>
<p>One of the biggest and most troubling technical issues we faced is that the Panic Button app has on occasion alerted people’s contacts without them triggering it intentionally. Given that the app was still in “beta” — meaning it was still in test phase — we took pains to warn people about this from when it was first brought to our attention. We also worked hard with our partners <a href="https://iilab.org">iilab</a> to find a solution to fix it.</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/news/panic-button-trigger-alert.png" />

</div>
<p>Unfortunately, after multi-month efforts, we have had to acknowledge that it is not an issue with a simple solution. That’s because the false alerts are not actually caused by any technical fault in the software. The app is actually behaving exactly as it was programmed to.</p>
<p>To explain: one of the features that many human rights defenders told us was essential to making Panic Button useful for them, was the ability to trigger the alert without having to open up the app, which would take time and be difficult in an emergency. In response, we decided to make the phone’s power button the trigger for the app. All it took was five fast presses of the power button and the alert messages would start sending once the app was set-up and active.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, pressing the power button on Android is directly linked to the phone’s screen turning on and off (this is a limitation of working within the operating system). This means that anytime the phone’s screen lights up and switches off, it is technically counted as one press of the power button.</p>
<p>As it turns out, there are several things that can trigger a phone screen lighting up and off in quick succession. One of the most frequent is when a phone receives a large number of SMS messages at the same time. This often happens when people use top-up credit, as mobile operators send multiple promotions and updates at the same time (a common way a lot of our users use their phones).</p>
<p>Because we were working within a constraint of the operating system, our hope was to try and reduce “false positives” (unwanted triggers) by changing the trigger pattern to something less likely to occur accidentally (you can see some of the <a href="https://docs.google.com/drawings/d/1xqpzIMjEnryB3hVZfGk2_fKyy97PYNnucoPRrF6vg_M/edit">trigger patterns that we explored here</a>).</p>
<p>Unfortunately, we were unable to find a solution that would reduce false positives without seriously compromising on usability. Each new barrier we added to stop unwanted alerts ran the risk of making the app less useful for activists who needed be able to trigger the alert easily and swiftly in an emergency. We tested out some of our solutions with activists in Nairobi last year. Based on their feedback, we decided we were not willing to make changes that while reducing one problem, simply increased another: the app’s usability.</p>
<h2 id="panic-features-for-the-future">Panic features for the future</h2>
<p>Panic Button has remained in a limbo for too long as we tried to seek a solution. Now as we look around at a lively ecosystem of security apps and tools, we recognize that Amnesty can have a greater impact promoting and advocating for “panic features” that work across devices and languages, rather than trying to develop our own app.</p>
<p>There are now countless Panic Button apps on the Google Play Store and many of them are better resourced, allowing them to scale for more phones and in a greater number of languages.</p>
<p>Some companies have also taken steps to build “emergency alert” features into their operating systems. For example, Samsung introduced <a href="https://www.androidcentral.com/how-use-emergency-features-samsung-galaxy-s7">SOS messages on the Galaxy S6</a>. The feature shares a lot with Panic Button, including sending a map link with the user’s coordinates, the ability to trigger the feature from the phone’s power button, and the ability to choose up to 3 emergency contacts. It also includes features that we were planning for future releases of Panic Button, such as the option to send pictures and an audio recording as attachments in the emergency messages.</p>
<p><img src="/images/news/panic-button-android-SOS.png" style="width: 168px; height: 300px; margin: 0 40%"/></p>
<p>We would like to see other phone makers follow Samsung’s lead, as ultimately this kind of feature would be useful to a far greater number of people if it was embedded in every handset alongside other routine features like airplane mode. We are calling on Google and Apple to make the SOS feature happen across all phones using their respective OSes (something which tech blog <a href="https://boingboing.net/2016/08/11/the-emergency-mode-every.html">Boing Boing has also called for</a>).</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/news/panic-button-iOS-emergency.png" />

</div>
<p>So far, Apple’s announcement of new features to iOS11 don’t go far enough. While they do include an Emergency SOS option, which can be triggered by pressing the Sleep/Wake button five times, at the moment this simply dials emergency services, which for human rights activists is less useful than being able to alert their own network. Apple should expand the utility of this feature by letting users choose their own emergency contacts, empowering them to develop a strong emergency response plan with their trusted networks.</p>
<h2 id="so-what-next">So, what next?</h2>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/news/panic-button-training-drawing.png" />

</div>
<p>When we started Panic Button, it was an idea that needed testing in the real world: the idea that a mobile alert app could be a simple but effective tool for human rights defenders at risk. Five years on, and we’re more confident than ever of the need that underpins Panic Button. We have been in security trainings and workshops all over the world where we have heard about the crippling daily insecurity of HRDs. We have been heartened to see that a simple tool can trigger concrete, practical conversations with HRDs about emergency response plans.</p>
<p>Planning for a situation that you hope will never happen is not easy, but these conversations are also necessary. We repeatedly saw that the concept of the PACT was invaluable, helping defenders face scenarios they should never have to face, and, in doing so, empowering them to take back some control of their security.</p>
<p>We will be building on these learnings by integrating the PACT methodology more deeply into Amnesty’s long-standing work with human rights defenders. We will be further building on the online training kit and interactive game we developed (<a href="https://panicbutton.io/pact-activities/pact-activities-04-impact-game.html">imPACT</a>) with the hope that these can become staple tools for facilitating emergency response planning in the human rights field.</p>
<p>As to the future of the app itself, while we are ceasing support for the app, the <a href="https://github.com/PanicInitiative/PanicButton">code is all still available on Github</a>. This includes some features that have been worked on but not released, for any adventurous developers out there.</p>
<p>For developers interested in contributing to advancing “panic features” more generally, there are other great efforts from open source mobile developers with the same care for human rights defenders that need more support. For example, we have worked closely with the Guardian Project in the past couple of years on their <a href="https://guardianproject.info/2016/01/12/panickit-making-your-whole-phone-respond-to-a-panic-button/">Panic Kit initiative</a>, which aims to make your whole phone respond to an emergency by locking down certain apps to protect your data.</p>
<p>Amnesty International and iilab will also continue to advocate for panic features in more handsets , so that one day every mobile phone will double as an alert system without the need to download an app. This would not only be valuable for human rights defenders, but it would also be a useful feature for anyone facing a situation of risk. We will also be pushing for Google and Apple to integrate a panic function that will work across their operating systems and be as simple and intuitive as airplane mode.</p>
<p>Ultimately, while we are sad as the Panic Button app experiment draws to a close, we are satisfied it has helped many HRDs across the world to rethink their security planning — while advancing a framework for doing so that we hope will long outlive the app.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.org/news/2017-09-03-panic-button-lessons-learned.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>@mckinneyjames Countless innovations in health / education / safety / etc. were first tested / demonstrated in the social sector. I see this as yet another example</title>
    <link>https://iilab.orghttps://twitter.com/mckinneyjames/status/903793634750943233</link>
    <description><![CDATA[]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.orghttps://twitter.com/mckinneyjames/status/903793634750943233</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Panic Button: Why we are retiring the app</title>
    <link>https://iilab.org/news/2017-09-01-panic-button-retiring-the-app.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p><em>This post is by <a href="https://twitter.com/TanyaOCarroll">Tanya O’Carroll</a>, Adviser Tech and Human Rights, Amnesty International; <a href="https://twitter.com/Ingleton">Danna Ingleton</a>, Adviser, Human Rights Defenders; and <a href="https://iilab.org/#team">Jun Matsushita</a>, Founder and CEO, iilab.</em></p>
<p><em>In 2012, <a href="http://amnesty.org">Amnesty International</a>, with support from our partners at <a href="http://iilab.org">iilab</a>, <a href="https://www.theengineroom.org">The Engine Room</a> and <a href="https://www.frontlinedefenders.org/">Frontline Defenders</a>, began developing a tool that would provide human rights defenders with an alert system in their pocket: the Panic Button app. Now, we’ve made the decision to cease ongoing support for the app. Here, we share the lessons learned and what it means for the future of developing security tools for human rights activists. .</em></p>
<!--more-->
<h2 id="the-origins-of-panic-button">The origins of Panic Button</h2>
<p>When we first called on the tech community to help us use technology to prevent unlawful detentions — back in 2012 — we always knew we would be trying something different. That was Amnesty International’s first Open Innovation Challenge; it was the first time the organization attempted to use technology to address human rights abuses directly.</p>
<p>Our dream was to develop a smart and simple tool that would provide human rights defenders (HRDs) with an alert system in their pocket: the panic button app.</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/news/pb-origins.png" />

</div>
<p>A huge, collaborative effort came out of that dream. About 350 designers and developers took part in an open design process, and multiple hackathons and codejams over a year and a half to prototype and develop the app. There were three iterations of the UX as we responded to the feedback and input of human rights defenders in Amnesty’s networks. 120 HRDs from 17 countries took part in in a six-month pilot and helped us understand how the app was working – or not working! – for them in practice (an <a href="https://www.amnesty.org/en/documents/act10/2133/2015/en/">evaluation of the pilot can be found here</a>).</p>
<p>We were also lucky to benefit from the insights and wisdom of a small group of amazing partners at <a href="https://iilab.org/">iilab</a>, <a href="https://www.frontlinedefenders.org/">Frontline Defenders</a> and <a href="https://www.theengineroom.org">The Engine Room</a>.</p>
<p>From the outset, all those involved knew this was about much more than an app. At its centre, the Panic Button project aimed to develop a model for strong peer-to-peer emergency response between HRDs and their networks. We worked closely with defenders from across the world to understand and build upon their existing security practices, designing a flexible security framework that would help them prepare for and manage physical threats. We called this security framework the PACT so that HRDs and their networks would be “Prepared to ACT.”</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/news/pb-participants.png" />

</div>
<p><em>A participant at a Panic Button workshop creates a map of countries where we tested Panic Button in partnership with the <a href="https://www.defenddefenders.org/">East and Horn of Africa Human Rights Defenders</a> Project in 2014.</em></p>
<h2 id="why-we-are-sunsetting-panic-button">Why we are sunsetting Panic Button</h2>
<p>Five years later and we have many stories of successes, failures and lessons learned. It would be worrying if we didn’t; it would mean that we hadn’t really tried anything new. We are proud of what we achieved with the PACT — and <a href="https://panicbutton.io/#pact">the training kit that supports it</a> — which represent an innovative approach to emergency response planning with HRDs. This has been confirmed over and over again in the feedback we have received from activists in trainings (some of the testimony from HRDs can be found <a href="http://panicalert.tumblr.com/">here in our training diary</a>).</p>
<p>Unfortunately, despite a huge collective effort, we have had to come to terms with the fact that the Panic Button app has not become the tool we hoped it would be. That’s why today we are making the painful decision, after months of pursuing all other avenues, to cease our support for the Panic Button app.</p>
<p>We arrived at that decision for three reasons:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Despite our best efforts, we have not been able to secure any substantial external funding for the project since being awarded £100,000 as runners-up in the Google Global Impact Award in June 2013. In part, this is due to what in hindsight was a short-lived boom in funding and excitement around “tech 4 good.”</li>
<li>Without adequate resourcing, we have not been able to resolve a major technical issue with the app: a false alert problem caused by “false positives” when the phone thinks the power button has been triggered.</li>
<li>Also linked to resourcing, we have not been able to keep up with the level of human resources needed to maintain our engagement with users.</li>
</ol>
<p>We think a lot of our experiences will be familiar to others who have experimented with developing tech for social good. We also think that failures too often get swept under the carpet. We don’t want to do that. Two months ago, we joined a session at the Internet Freedom Festival in Valencia to <a href="https://internetfreedomfestival.org/wiki/index.php/Panic_button_apps_%26_the_thin_line_between_online_%26_offline_security_for_journalists_and_HR_defenders">share lessons from the Panic Button experience</a>. This post builds off the discussions we had with many of you there.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We also think that failures too often get swept under the carpet. We don’t want to do that.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We hope our experience provides useful lessons for app developers, human rights technologists and funders, and contributes towards tech initiatives that are scalable, sustainable and socially impactful.</p>
<p>We also owe it to our users, and the many friends of this project, to provide a proper explanation as to why, even after all our best efforts, the Panic Button app has not worked. For that reason, we dedicated <a href="https://www.theengineroom.org/panic-button-lessons-learned/">our next post to taking a closer look at the challenges the Panic Button app faced and ultimately could not overcome.</a></p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2017 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.org/news/2017-09-01-panic-button-retiring-the-app.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Deep dive into Rainwater Harvesting</title>
    <link>https://iilab.org/news/2017-04-21-rainwater-harvesting.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>In this video, filmed during the third Engineering Comes Home co-design workshop, participants explored in more depth implementation of the chosen idea: rainwater harvesting.</p>
<!--more-->
<p><br></p>
<center>
<div class="iframeWrapper">
<iframe width="100%" height="*" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/PsaspQ3wBrE?showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
</div>
</center>
<p><br></p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2017 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.org/news/2017-04-21-rainwater-harvesting.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>London community using our prototype Nexus Calculator</title>
    <link>https://iilab.org/news/2016-11-26-nexus-calculator.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Today, in an Estate near London Bridge in the UK, a community of inhabitants from an estate used our prototype Nexus Calculator to discuss various design options for food sharing, food growing, collecting rainwater or composting on the estate. This is the second time our team meets this community, as part of the Engineering Comes Home project in partnership with University College London and <a href="https://openlab.ncl.ac.uk">Open Lab</a> at Newcastle University we <a href="/blog/communities-codesigning-infrastructure">blogged about a few months ago</a>.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>Based on the inputs from the first workshop and building on an LCA assessment spreadsheet developed by one of the project’s researchers, iilab developed a prototype which aims at supporting decision making of communities when it comes to infrastructure design. The project’s key deliverable is a toolkit for infrastructure designers, which will outline different approaches to engage communities on infrastructure.</p>
<center>
<div class="iframeWrapper">
<iframe width="100%" height="*" src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/JcF1VU5aCw0?showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
</div>
</center>
<p><br></p>
<h1 id="in-the-workshop">In the Workshop</h1>
<p>We presented the five ideas, providing participants with fact sheets about each one and showing them how to use the LCA calculator to assess different design criteria. The calculator had a scenario for each technology with adjustable input parameters such as volume of food waste, quantity and scale of technologies. These changed the volume of food that could be grown, or amount of CO2 savings realised. Residents explored each scenario in pairs adjusting the calculator according to their assessment of what was appropriate for the estate. These context sensitive adjustments included:</p>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Levels community involvement:</strong> For example, Clare, who’d been involved in other community projects on the estate made an assessment that only 50% of households would participate and went on to limit inputs to this proportion of engagement for all scenarios. By contrast Penny decided the technologies could be designed to increase engagement in some cases. For the waste compactor, she opted to put small manual compactors at each of the stairwells on the basis that residents would then regularly see them and be encouraged to use them.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Aesthetics and layout of the estate:</strong> Participants used their knowledge of the estate, and of the ways communal space was used by different members of the community. This was particularly the case in the gardening scenarios. Participants anchored their designs in which parts of the estate gardens they would be happy to see turned into food growing areas.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Utility of outputs:</strong> Although the LCA calculator was designed to show the resulting CO2 emissions reductions, these savings were not a very meaningful currency for the group. Instead the designs were more often shaped according to whether the outputs could be used. For example, when assessing the options for the wormeries, Mary was interested in how much fertiliser could be produced and whether the TRA would be able to sell or exchange this amongst other local gardening groups.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>After participants had explored each scenario we regrouped and discussed the design options each pair had chosen. This allowed the group to share the different priorities and assessments that had informed their adjustments of the LCA calculator parameters. After the groups had explored all five ideas we held a vote to pick a single design option to move forward with. The discussion prior to the vote gave space for participants to raise other context specific values and knowledge they felt should be factored into the group’s selection of a design. Governance proved to be a key concern, in particular how much management any design would require, and also how exposed the system would be to tampering from ‘uninitiated outsiders’. For example waste compacting was seen as potentially dangerous if people didn’t know how to use the compactor properly, likewise food sharing was felt to be open to mismanagement. All participants had a first and second vote and rainwater harvesting won the most votes.</p>
<div class="figure">
<img src="/images/news/ech_workshop2_votes.png" />

</div>
<h1 id="functional-core">Functional core</h1>
<p>With regards to the technology, our team decided to go with a functional core using Purescript (a Haskell derivative which is well adapted to the frontend) in order to benefit from static types to assist in having correct calculations for the modeled processes. We iterated a few times on the data model and settled on a static representation of each scenarios, to avoid the complexity of a completely modular system where the user can pick and choose freely from a set of Processes.</p>
<p>We also decided to go for an “double-entry accounting model” of material flows, with an approach close to Event Sourcing (<a href="https://openintegrity.org/blog/">which we’re using in Open Integrity as well</a>), where each Process debits upstream processes for the amount of supply they need, credit themselves of this amount, then possibly draw down on the amount on their accounts to transform it into another material which can in turn be drawn from by other downstream processes. This lightweight model seemed adequate for giving broad indications on quantities and wrapping the information in the LCA spreadsheet in an accessible way. Each Process is also a pure function which takes a “ledger” of all material transactions and returns an updated ledger. Although we haven’t tested it quite yet, this should allow loops to occur in the graph, for instance when food produced by a Food Garden is diminishing the needed supply of shopped food.</p>
<h1 id="research">Research</h1>
<p>Engineering Comes Home demonstrated that residents were willing and able to play a meaningful role in the design of neighbourhood scale infrastructure. We started the co-design workshops with a blank sheet in terms of what form our WEF nexus intervention might take and ended with a rainwater tank and hose providing water for the TRA’s flower beds. This specific design solution evolved from the participants’ broad concern with wastefulness and the value of pioneering water stewardship.</p>
<p>The co-design process was iterative and responsive to the context. Through it we have found:</p>
<ul>
<li>A willingness to engage in the co-design process</li>
<li>That people are motivated by the idea of saving WEF resources beyond rational choice models of motivation</li>
<li>We could generate a set of shared values to create a design brief</li>
<li>It was possible to build technical literacy amongst participants</li>
</ul>
<p>The pilot has allowed us to test the process and learn from this first case-study. Following the principles of co-design, the lessons learnt have been distilled into a set of co-design method statements which are freely available for others to use and build on. This first case-study provides an encouraging example of how residents can be included in the technical work of creating less resource intense, more liveable cities.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.org/news/2016-11-26-nexus-calculator.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Engineering Comes Home to test new paradigms in infrastructure engineering</title>
    <link>https://iilab.org/news/2016-01-06-communities-codesigning-infrastructure.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Sustainability. Resilience. Scarcity. Climate change. When it comes to resources recently we’re worrying that they are going to run out, and about the impact of waste from their consumption.</p>
<p>At iilab we’ve been working on understanding the systems around water with our mapping of the <a href="https://kumu.io/iilab/ofwat-resilience-systems-map">UK water systems</a> and contributions to the <a href="https://iilab.org/news/2015-12-01-recommendations-water-sector-open-data-citizen-stewardship.html">Ofwat Resilience Task and Finish Group last year</a>, and with <a href="https://iilab.org/projects/open-droplet.html">Open Droplet</a>. These projects look at water from a systems and from an end-user standpoint, aiming to see water resources and wastewater in a holistic manner.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>Unwittingly, our outlook has addressed a prevalent problem in infrastructure design - for water and other resources consumed in a domestic environment - where the home is normally treated as a “black box”. It’s an issue we first came across in discussions with <a href="https://iris.ucl.ac.uk/iris/browse/profile?upi=SJBEL56">Dr Sarah Bell</a> at University College London’s Engineering Department, and we’re excited to be tackling it again, this time with Dr Bell and her team, with a new project launched late last year.</p>
<p>With University College London and <a href="https://openlab.ncl.ac.uk">Open Lab</a> at Newcastle University, we have just launched the Engineering Comes Home project, which addresses the complex interplay at the nexus of human interaction with water, food, energy and waste while changing the paradigm of understanding the problem space. Engineering Comes Home aims to be a proof of concept for including community co-design practices into infrastructure design.</p>
<p>We’ll collectively be bringing ethnography, HCI, lifecycle assessment, engineering, design, research, tech and rapid prototyping to the space to develop a Co-Design Toolkit for Infrastructure Design.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2016 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.org/news/2016-01-06-communities-codesigning-infrastructure.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Ten recommendations to make the water sector more resilient - open data and citizen stewardship</title>
    <link>https://iilab.org/news/2015-12-01-recommendations-water-sector-open-data-citizen-stewardship.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>How do we make a difference to water resilience? Today’s report, published by Ofwat and compiled by the independent Water Resilience Task and Finish Group, contains ten UK-focussed recommendations for improving water resilience.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The recommendations in brief are:</p>
<ol style="list-style-type: decimal">
<li>Agree a shared definition of resilience for the sector.</li>
<li>Increase public engagement and education</li>
<li>Ensure clear routes for funding legitimate resilience measures</li>
<li>Ensure coherent planning for resilience at both a national and regional level</li>
<li>Establish wastewater, sewerage and drainage plans</li>
<li>Improve understanding of risk and failure</li>
<li>Ensure services are resilient under different water sector structures</li>
<li>Develop benchmarking, standards and metrics</li>
<li>Ensure existing plans are stress-tested</li>
<li>Establish a water and wastewater resilience action group</li>
</ol>
<p>You can <a href="http://www.ofwat.gov.uk/wp-content/uploads/2015/12/rpt_com20151201resiliencetaskfinish.pdf">read and download the report from the Ofwat website</a>.</p>
<h2 id="open-data-and-citizen-stewardship-of-water-resources">Open data and citizen stewardship of water resources</h2>
<p>I’ve been part of the Task and Finish group over the last year, and you may remember that <a href="https://iilab.org/news/2015-07-28-uk-water-resilience.html">we launched a call for participation earlier this year</a>. Thank you to everyone who contributed. I’m thrilled that the recommendations contain calls for open data and greater citizen agency have been included in the report:</p>
<p><em><strong>2. Increase public engagement and education</strong></em><br> <em>When: 2015 - 2020</em><br> <em>Lead: Water companies and governments</em><br> <em>Involved: All sector and non sector partners, including stakeholders and third parties</em><br> <em>Using a common definition, or set of definitions, there is a need to engage the wider public, particularly in relation to risk, and to develop a common understanding of the acceptability of risk. This engagement should be twofold.</em><br> <em>Firstly it should involve the provision of pertinent information on a wide scale on an ongoing basis, with the aim of enhancing public understanding of water systems. Secondly it should aim to ensure this information is transformed into active engagement (which will lead to positive environmental behaviour) - the public should be given an active role in resilience, both in terms of adaptation and mitigation.</em><br> <em>The action to deliver this recommendation sits with all bodies in the sector. But it sits primarily with water companies who must undertake much more active engagement and with governments who, whilst they are unlikely to do any public outreach in this area, must reinstate areas where they have removed information provision, like the reintroduction of the water cycle as a key element of the national curriculum. The water sector should, where possible, continue to increase access to data, subject to commercial confidentiality and security exemptions. The sector strategic dashboard currently being developed by water companies, regulators and other stakeholders could be a helpful contribution to facilitating that access. More open data would assist better public understanding and engagement and could promote innovation and understanding and increase resilience through crowd sourced solutions and oversight.</em><br></p>
<p>and</p>
<p><em><strong>6. Improve the understanding of risk and failure When: 2015 - 2020</strong></em><br> <em>Lead: Environment Agency, Natural Resources Wales, water companies</em><br> <em>There needs to be broad discussion, involving all parties including customers, leading to agreement on the level of service which should be planned for in each area. This would be based on better understanding and communication of the risks faced by the water sector, of the costs of failure, and of the costs and benefits of measures to avert, manage and recover from failure. Coping strategies for dealing with ‘beyond resilience’ emergencies (black swan events) also need to be agreed, in advance of their occurrence. Progress in these matters will enable water companies to focus on the risks to critical assets and services, and to plan for the effective delivery of services in critical conditions, with a mandate from their customers and society, and from their regulators and government.</em><br> <em>Another requirement is an appreciation by all that some failures will occur, notwithstanding best plans being laid and large investment being made; for example, expecting zero leakage and never having supply interruptions is unhelpful thinking.</em><br> <em>Risk could also be better understood and dealt with through more open data, enabling wider scrutiny of water and wastewater management. This could link to the sector strategic dashboard that is currently under development.</em><br></p>
<h2 id="get-your-hands-wet">Get your hands wet</h2>
<p>These points around facilitating citizen stewardship of water and increased open data from the water sector, while hard-won, are backed up by current academic literature on resilience, and a systems map that we’ve been working on on the kumu platform. They’re issues we’ve also discussed previously, for instance in <a href="https://iilab.org/news/2014-11-02-open-droplet-lote4.html">our session at LOTE4 The Stewardship</a>. If open data and citizen stewardship of water are important to you, please add your voice and action to making these changes real. We’re particularly interested to hear about projects where there is community stewardship of resources. <script type="text/javascript">
<!--
h='&#x69;&#x69;&#108;&#x61;&#98;&#46;&#x6f;&#114;&#x67;';a='&#64;';n='&#x63;&#x6f;&#110;&#116;&#x61;&#x63;&#116;';e=n+a+h;
document.write('<a h'+'ref'+'="ma'+'ilto'+':'+e+'" clas'+'s="em' + 'ail">'+'&#x47;&#x65;&#116;&#32;&#x69;&#110;&#32;&#116;&#x6f;&#x75;&#x63;&#104;&#32;&#x77;&#x69;&#116;&#104;&#32;&#x75;&#x73;&#32;&#104;&#x65;&#114;&#x65;&#32;&#x61;&#116;&#32;&#x69;&#x69;&#108;&#x61;&#98;'+'<\/'+'a'+'>');
// -->
</script><noscript>&#x47;&#x65;&#116;&#32;&#x69;&#110;&#32;&#116;&#x6f;&#x75;&#x63;&#104;&#32;&#x77;&#x69;&#116;&#104;&#32;&#x75;&#x73;&#32;&#104;&#x65;&#114;&#x65;&#32;&#x61;&#116;&#32;&#x69;&#x69;&#108;&#x61;&#98;&#32;&#40;&#x63;&#x6f;&#110;&#116;&#x61;&#x63;&#116;&#32;&#x61;&#116;&#32;&#x69;&#x69;&#108;&#x61;&#98;&#32;&#100;&#x6f;&#116;&#32;&#x6f;&#114;&#x67;&#x29;</noscript>, or <a href="http://twitter.com/home?status=Calling%20for%20#opendata%20and%20#peoplepower%20for%20#water%20#resilience%20cc%20@iilab%20https://bit.ly/resilience-water">tweet this post</a>.</p>
<p>We’re still working on the water resilience systems map. A static version is included in the report, and shown above. We’d like to invite you to <a href="https://kumu.io/iilab/ofwat-resilience-systems-map">contribute to building the map further by collaborating with us on kumu</a>. We’re sure there are more insights we can get out of this mapping - ones that will be relevant globally.</p>
<p><a href="https://kumu.io/iilab/ofwat-resilience-systems-map">Collaborate on the Water Resilience Systems map on kumu</a>.</p>
<h2 id="water-resilience---what-the-papers-say">Water resilience - what the papers say</h2>
<p>Meanwhile, if you have a more academic interest in water resilience, I compiled this literature review for the report. While the report is now closed, our interest in this topic is still as keen as ever. Please join the conversation if you have feedback that we can move forward with.</p>
<h3 id="resilience-of-water-systems">Resilience of water systems</h3>
<p>Like any complex system, resilience of water systems can be defined in terms of their response to specific threats over time (Haimes, 2009). Many factors are implicated in water resilience (Matthews, 2015), such as water scarcity for both green and blue water, water quality, flooding, waste water, salinisation, and economic scarcity where social resources required to successfully adapt to physical water scarcity fall short (Ohlsson, 2000), and it is the factors that feed into their provision that determines the resilience of the system with respect to a particular threat. A distinction can be made between man-made resilience issues, and those that occur naturally - for instance water scarcity as a result of natural conditions of low water availability in comparison to water scarcity mainly induced by a large human demand relative to natural availability (which can also happen in water abundant areas) (Schyns et al, 2015). This is an engineering resilience perspective, and one which has been largely adopted by the UK in its approach to resilience more broadly, and in this report. In the literature, alternative views of resilience exist, for instance a more socio-ecological view of resilience looks at resilience of a system in terms of the repurcussions on both human needs and ecosystem needs, seeing them as intrinsically linked. In such cases resilience is defined not as how well a system recovers from or adapts to events, but in terms of “the amount of disturbance a linked social-ecological system can absorb before reorganizing into a new state characterized by a different set of processes and structures.” (Garmestani et al. 2014).</p>
<p>In order to solve resilience problems in such a complex system, it is necessary to move away from focussing on components in the system to looking at the system’s interconnectedness (Helbing et al, 2012), including links to systems that may be seen as discrete, such as the electricity network (Matthews, 2015) or a country’s legal framework (Garmestani et al., 2014). Approaches to water resilience in the scientific literature call for solutions as multifaceted and complex as the water system itself (Wong and Brown, 2009, Kennedy et al. 2012, Ashley et al 2003, 2005). As Kennedy et al. write: “Building resilience is not simply an engineering problem involving more dams and canals. It is a socioeconomic phenomenon that requires a highly interdisciplinary approach, including analysis of governance and social systems, as well as hydrology.” (Kennedy et al. 2012). In this direction, access to a diversity of water resources, including centralised and decentralised sources, is argued by Wong and Brown to be a resilient approach for water sensitive cities (Wong and Brown, 2009) and, in a similar vein, the urban harvest approach, which taps into both primary and secondary water resources at a local level, has proved effective in both the Netherlands and Australia as an aid for sustainable urban resource planning (Agudelo-Vera et al 2012).</p>
<p>Kennedy et al. also suggest thinking across geographical boundaries in terms of resource management. Novel technological approaches can provide greater efficiency in the allocation of scarce resources (Anzaldi, 2014, Helbing et al., 2012) and quick response to threats such as flooding (Young-Il and Kim, 2015) and water quality measurements (Shin et al., 2009). Yet, the strategies by which these technological advances are leveraged must be carefully chosen as there is a risk that the “smart city” paradigm will be pushed forward not for the purposes of resource efficiency, but rather for promotion of consumption of digital goods, resulting in ineffective interventions in resource use obfuscating an actual lessening or absence of effect on resilience (Viitanen and Kingston, 2014)</p>
<p>In terms of governance and social systems, Ostrom has shown that collective governance of resources, including water resources, has success on a local scale (Ostrom, 1990). Here, the advent of big data can be of use in facilitating a more integrated approach to governance by leveraging social interest. Open data and citizen science approaches can augment water treatment and provision services (Buckingham Shum et al.), and lessons from disaster response in Kathmandu suggest that local open data ecosystems can aide rapid response to events (Soden et al., 2014).</p>
<h3 id="references">References</h3>
<p>Agudelo-Vera C., Mels A., Keesman K., and Rijnaarts H.. 2012. The Urban Harvest Approach as an Aid for Sustainable Urban Resource Planning, Journal of Industrial Ecology, Volume 16, Issue 6, 839–850</p>
<p>Ashley, R. M., Balmforth, D. J., Saul, A. J. &amp; Blanksby, J. R. 2005 Flooding in the future. Water Sci. Technol. 52(5), 265–274.</p>
<p>Ashley, R. M., Blackwood, D. J., Butler, D., Davies, J. A., Jowitt, P. &amp; Smith, H. 2003 Sustainable decision making for the UK water industry. Eng. Sustainability 156(ES1), 41–49.</p>
<p>Buckingham Shum, S.; Aberer, K.; Schmidt, A.; Bishop, S.; Lukowicz, P.; Anderson, S.; Charalabidis, Y.; Domingue, D.; de Freitas, S.; Dunwell, I.; Edmonds, B.; Grey, F.; Haklay, M.; Jelasity, M.; Karpiˇstˇsenko, A.; Kohlhammer, J.; Lewis, J.; Pitt, J.; Sumner, R. and Helbing, D. (2012). Towards a global participatory platform: democratising open data, complexity science and collective intelligence. European Physical Journal Special Topics, 214(1), pp. 109–152.</p>
<p>Garmestani, Ahjond S.; Allen, Craig R.; Arnold, Craig Anthony (Tony); and Gunderson, Lance H., “Introduction: Social-Ecological Resilience and Law” (2014). Nebraska Cooperative Fish &amp; Wildlife Research Unit – Staff Publications. Paper 142. http://digitalcommons.unl.edu/ncfwrustaff/142</p>
<p>Haimes, Y.Y. On the Definition of Resilience in Systems, Risk Analysis, Vol. 29, No. 4, 2009, 498-501</p>
<p>Helbing D., S. Bishop, R. Conte, P. Lukowicz, and J.B. McCarthy, FuturICT: Participatory computing to understand and manage our complex world in a more sustainable and resilient way, Eur. Phys. J. Special Topics 214, 11–39 (2012)</p>
<p>Kennedy C., Baker L., Dhakal S., Ramaswami A., Sustainable Urban Systems, Journal of Industrial Ecology, 16, 6, 2012, 775-779</p>
<p>Matthews J.C., Disaster Resilience of Critical Water Infrastructure Systems, Journal of Structural Engineering, C6015001, DOI: 10.1061/(ASCE)ST.1943-541X.0001341 ,</p>
<p>Ohlsson, L, Water conflicts and social resource scarcity, Physics and Chemistry of the Earth, Part B: Hydrology, Oceans and Atmosphere, Volume 25, Issue 3, 2000, 213–220</p>
<p>Ostrom E., Governing the Commons (CUP, 1990) Schyns J.F., Hoekstra A.Y., Boolj M.J., Review and classification of indicators of green water availability and scarcity, Hydrology and Earth Systems Sciences Discources, 12, 5519-5594, 2015</p>
<p>Shin, P., Song, Y., Choi, Y., and Park, Y. (2009) Seoul (Korea) Online Water Quality Monitoring of Drinking Water. World Environmental and Water Resources Congress 2009: pp. 1-9.</p>
<p>Soden R., Budhathoki N., Palen L. Resilience-Building and the Crisis Informatics Agenda: Lessons Learned from Open Cities Kathmandu, Proceedings of the 11th International ISCRAM Conference, 339-348, 2014 g Viitanen J. and Kingston R., 2014 Environ Plan A, April 2014 vol. 46 no. 4 803-819</p>
<p>Young-Il and Kim, 2015 http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2015EGUGA..17.8193M</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Dec 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.org/news/2015-12-01-recommendations-water-sector-open-data-citizen-stewardship.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Countdown 2030 - Citizen Science Challenges and Opportunities</title>
    <link>https://iilab.org/news/2015-11-30-countdown-2030.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Citizen science is a pretty wonderful phenomenon that is changing the dynamics of knowledge generation in the same way that open access is changing the dynamics of knowledge ownership. So how can we make it even better?</p>
<!--more-->
<p>The next step in citizen science is to incorporate different aspects of design - particularly ideas around embodied cognition, social development theory and human centric design. Why? Because the next step in the citizen science journey is to anchor it more fully in lived experience, to help citizen science and its enabling technology to create bridges between people and a lens through which to understand the world’s complexity.</p>
<p>I expand on these ideas in this talk, which was presented remotely at <a href="http://www.igp.ucl.ac.uk/igp-events-pub/countdown-2030">UCL’s Institute of Global Prosperity’s Countdown 2030 conference</a> on Saturday. The conference had an amazing line-up, looking at the advances being brought by young researchers that could have a significant impact on the development of science and society in the next 15 years. It was an honour to be part of the line-up organised by <a href="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/excites/people/academic-staff/muki-haklay">Muki Haklay of UCL ExCITES</a>.</p>
<p>Here’s the video of the recorded presentation:</p>
<center>
<div class="iframeWrapper">
<div class="video-container post-media">
<iframe src="//player.vimeo.com/video/147366069?color=506a85" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
<p>
<a href="http://vimeo.com/147366069">Countdown 2030 - Citizen Science Challenges and Opportunities</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/iilab">iilab</a> on <a href="https://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a>.
</p>
</div>
</div>
</center>
<p><br></p>
<p>And here are the slides with the transcript below, including some references:</p>
<center>
<div class="iframeWrapper">
<iframe src="//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/55640817" width="100%" height="600" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;" allowfullscreen>
</iframe>
<div style="margin-bottom:5px">
<strong> <a href="//www.slideshare.net/KatAusten/countdown2030-kat-austen" title="Countdown 2030 - Kat Austen" target="_blank">Countdown 2030 - Kat Austen</a> </strong> from <strong><a href="//www.slideshare.net/katausten" target="_blank">Kat Austen</a></strong>
</div>
</div>
</center>
<p><br></p>
<p>I want to talk about 2 aspects that I think could prove fruitful for citizen science now and in the future, namely creating a richer experience of data, and human-centered design. I’ll then open it up to more creative thoughts about the role of citizen science in our future society.</p>
<ul>
<li>Data can be misleading, and datasets need to be richer to help provide context.</li>
<li>Squashing a rich dataset into one node or line can lead to loss of information or misrepresentation</li>
<li>It’s also the case that diifferent modes of interaction with the data can produce different insights and behaviours. We understand the world - and data - in part from our physical interactions, and that aspect is something that’s is largely neglected.</li>
</ul>
<p><br></p>
<ul>
<li>We already know that the use of devices change how we think whether that’s in terms of spatial awareness, reasoning or interpretation</li>
<li>And we know that interacting with data through other senses uncovers different patterns in the data than visualisation - eg Brain Stethoscope by Parvisi and Chafe sonified EEG patterns as a more effective way to detect epileptic fits Epilepsy and Behaviour May 2015, Volume 46, Pages 53–54</li>
<li>We also make meaning of data through a cultural filter, so working with community interpretation of data also produces different insights and behaviours - something leveraged in citizen and DIY science.</li>
</ul>
<p>There are presently challenges in citizen science in terms of durability of projects - that is sustained engagement. A common question raised is also around the data quality - either from too few participants, from incomplete or sparse datasets, or poor adherence to scientific methodologies.</p>
<p>Finally, there are ethical and political considerations - in the worst case, citizen scientists can be viewed as unpaid data collectors, or in the case of gamified engagement as human ginuea pigs. Should citizens have more influence over citizen science projects than just funding them with taxes and contributing to them with their time? There’s also the possibility of missing out on the potential of innovation either in method or instrumentation, if citizen scientists are not fully engaged.</p>
<p>So, how do we make the most of citizen science projects for global prosperity? To do this we need to anchor citizen science in human experience, which should create greater understanding and more durable engagement.</p>
<p>I’m interested in using interdisciplinary methods to move into an even more human centred and holistic view of citizen science in a person’s life and in society. That translates into combining citizen science methods, with embodied experiences that put that our shared learning into context</p>
<p>Let me give you 2 examples of this in my work. One is from Piksel Festival in Bergen, Norway, and uses embodied cognition principles to create stronger relationships between citizens and the meaning of the data they produce in the course of their experiments.</p>
<p>With my collaborators, we’ve been working on developing tools to help anyone test for micro-plastics using household chemicals and equipment. We were also making and using DIY hydrophones to check for human-made sound pollution in the fjord.</p>
<p>From there we’ve also been working on informing a new way to engage with the data through design of a “coral empathy” prototype, which will eventually use the audio data captured by hydrophones to create and tune vibrations in a helmet. The microplastic pollution is translated into smells, which will be dialled up or down depending on the pollution that is detected.</p>
<p>My second example comes from my work at iilab, where we are working on centring first on the needs of the community and determining what data needs to be collected. In collaboration with UCL and Newcastle University’s Open Lab, we have recently launched the Engineering Comes Home project, where we’re investigating the use of community co-design methods in application to infrastructure engineering at the nexus of food, water, waste and energy resource use.</p>
<p>What data should be gathered is very open because there’s virtually no data around domestic and community behaviour around this nexus. We can let the community decide which indicators to focus on, hoping this will make the engagement sustainable, and to help the community engage with the politics of infrastructure.</p>
<p>In this project we will combine approaches from multiple disciplines alongside the knowledge from the community to understand and design for citizen sensing and intervention requirements.</p>
<p>Particularly pertinent for this project is the importance of creating a way to engage with the complexity of the interconnected food, waste, water and energy infrastructure systems, by designing prototype technologies that allow communities to connect with and intervene in these systems in a holistic way.</p>
<p>During the course of the project, it’s fundamental to create real links between people through the engagement with citizen science tools and data platforms. Here we can learn from work from community building with digital media - such as community forums and digital storytelling, and advances using tangible user interfaces for collaborative learning.</p>
<p>In 15 years, innovations from academia and hackerspaces alike will enable a more physical and emotive engagement with data gathering, processing and representation. This will make us more connected with our environment and will make complex systems easier to understand.</p>
<p>Science will be more integrated with society and politics, and both science and politics will be more participative. And people will feel more active and influential in the world they live in.</p>
<p>This more physical engagement with knowledge will create links between people, bringing people out of their data bubble. We will move beyond screens, beyond data, to a more integrated understanding and embodied experience of our knowledge - together.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.org/news/2015-11-30-countdown-2030.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>Help us make a new tool to guide network mappers</title>
    <link>https://iilab.org/news/2015-08-14-toolbox-network-mapping.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>We are surrounded by complex systems and power structures, not least of which are the networks of links between people by which they change and are changed. Understanding these links can sometimes have important consequences - for instance if you see that a policy-maker has strong personal ties to a lobbying organisation, you may see their decisions in a different light.</p>
<!--more-->
<p>Mapping these social networks of influence can be an important tool for researchers, journalists, activists and others. There are many tools and methods out there aiming to do just this, and for the last few months we’ve been actively engaging with the <a href="http://influencemapping.org">Influence Mappers</a> community, who are working to create standards and resources that help those trying to document relationships between people, organisations, and political processes.</p>
<h2 id="the-influence-mapping-toolbox">The Influence Mapping Toolbox</h2>
<p>Over the next few months, iilab will be working on developing the <a href="http://influencemapping.org/influence-mapping-toolbox/">Influence Mapping Toolbox</a>, which will help newcomers (and more experienced people too) get started, learn and achieve their influence mapping goals.</p>
<p>It will provide information about inspiring projects, as well as the different methods and tools available for different teams and goals. We will build it using a human centered approach and will make our results available as we progress.</p>
<p>Our team will be made up of Kat (me), Head of Research and Design, Lilas, Research Associate, and Jun.</p>
<h2 id="we-need-you">We need you!</h2>
<p>We want to hear from both the experienced influence mapping community and with people just starting out. Your feedback will help us better design the Influence Mapping Toolbox.</p>
<p>Just starting a project? Recently developed one or a few projects? <strong>We’d like to invite you to <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/149mqSqwxCWZDkBT2RhEph-H4ZyOudcWjhbi2Wffz0vU/viewform">answer our questionnaire</a></strong>.</p>
<p>It will only take 10 minutes of your time and will help a lot to build the toolbox. You also can get in touch directly via email to influencemapping@iilab.org or by following the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/influencemapping">Influence Mapping Google Group</a> thread.</p>
<p>From <strong>experienced practitioners</strong>, we’d particularly like to hear about:</p>
<ul>
<li>Thinking back to when you first started on your influence mapping project, what were the questions you had and what type of resource would you have wanted as a guide?</li>
<li>Do you know anyone who’s just getting started on an influence mapping project?</li>
</ul>
<p>For more information about our process, please check out the community’s <a href="http://influencemapping.org/influence-mapping-toolbox/">Influence Mapping Toolbox</a> announcement, or get in touch to have a chat at <script type="text/javascript">
<!--
h='&#x69;&#x69;&#108;&#x61;&#98;&#46;&#x6f;&#114;&#x67;';a='&#64;';n='&#x69;&#110;&#102;&#108;&#x75;&#x65;&#110;&#x63;&#x65;&#x6d;&#x61;&#112;&#112;&#x69;&#110;&#x67;';e=n+a+h;
document.write('<a h'+'ref'+'="ma'+'ilto'+':'+e+'" clas'+'s="em' + 'ail">'+e+'<\/'+'a'+'>');
// -->
</script><noscript>&#x69;&#110;&#102;&#108;&#x75;&#x65;&#110;&#x63;&#x65;&#x6d;&#x61;&#112;&#112;&#x69;&#110;&#x67;&#32;&#x61;&#116;&#32;&#x69;&#x69;&#108;&#x61;&#98;&#32;&#100;&#x6f;&#116;&#32;&#x6f;&#114;&#x67;</noscript>.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 14 Aug 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.org/news/2015-08-14-toolbox-network-mapping.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>
<item>
    <title>How do we make UK water provision more resilient?</title>
    <link>https://iilab.org/news/2015-07-28-uk-water-resilience.html</link>
    <description><![CDATA[<p>Open call for consultation from UK water regulator Ofwat as part of Kat’s work with the resilience working group</p>
<!--more-->
<p>As cultures we constantly evolve in our approach to different issues. In terms of human existence within our environment, we have transitioned from living embedded in and at the mercy of it, through processes of industrialisation, to environmentalism, and sustainability - and now we have now reached a concept of resilience that is prominent even at a policy level.</p>
<h2 id="the-ofwat-water-resilience-task-and-finish-group">The OFWAT Water Resilience Task and Finish Group</h2>
<p>In the UK this takes shape at government level in the form of directives that aim to improve resilience accross the country and in different sectors. This includes, among others, <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/collections/sector-resilience-plans">sector resilience plans</a>, <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/policies/emergency-planning">emergency planning</a> and risk assessment, <a href="https://www.gov.uk/resilience-in-society-infrastructure-communities-and-businesses">engagement with society</a>, and - in terms of water - the <a href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2014/21/contents/enacted">Water Act 2014</a>, which includes a <a href="http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/2014/21/part/1/chapter/3/crossheading/general-duties-of-the-water-services-regulation-authority/enacted">duty for the UK water regulator to secure resilience in the water sector</a>.</p>
<p>To understand how to fulfil this duty, the UK water regulator, <a href="http://ofwat.gov.uk">Ofwat</a>, convened at the start of 2015 the <a href="http://www.ofwat.gov.uk/regulating/tools/prs_web20150706resiliencetaskandfinish">Water Resilience Task and Finish Group</a>, chaired by <a href="http://www.waterwise.org.uk/pages/jacob-tompkins.html">Jacob Tompkins</a>, MD of <a href="http://www.waterwise.org.uk">Waterwise</a>. Jacob approached me to participate as a member of the group, alongside colleagues from within the water industry, academia and environmental organisations.</p>
<p>I am thrilled and humbled to be helping provide recommendations that may shape the UK’s approach to water resilience. With the group, I am working on two areas: a broad look at what water resilience looks like from a multitude of perspectives, which Jun and I are now turning into a map of water resilience with the aim of producing a systems map that can be used by policy makers and stakeholders alike to understand leverage points in which they could have agency to bring about a more resilient approach to water; and a body of research on community based water resilience strategies.</p>
<h2 id="working-towards-a-clear-definition-of-resilience">Working towards a clear definition of Resilience</h2>
<p>Defining resilience is almost a specialisation in itself, and no definition will please all the people all the time. But part of the workgroup’s aim is to come up with a workable definition that focusses on water resilience in the UK. Our work has already had an impact in shaping <a href="http://www.ofwat.gov.uk/regulating/tools/pap_con20150708resilence.pdf?download=Download">Ofwat’s definition of resilience in their resilience consultation,</a> which is taking place alongside our independent work.</p>
<p>The definition so far is:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Resilience is the ability to cope with, and recover from, disruption, trends and variability in order to maintain services for people and protect the natural environment, now and in the future.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><br></p>
<p>Being part of the working group is a valuable two way learning experience. With a perspective from outside the water sector, it’s been interesting for me to learn more about the national-scale processes in play. It’s also been interesting to see how community and citizens are perceived differently by different stakeholders in the discussion - for water companies the agency of a customer is predominantly through their ability or willingness to pay, whereas from my perspective - something that chimes with our work at iilab and Open Droplet - these customers are citizens with agency that can be acted in multiple ways either individually or as part of a community. This may take the form of engaging with their political representatives, their water company, as a community member working with organisations to prevent flooding or improve river water quality, or by taking steps to decentralise or create multiple modes for their water supply.</p>
<h2 id="unpacking-perspectives-on-resilience">Unpacking perspectives on Resilience</h2>
<p>Another interesting difference was how each of us perceived the “final point” at which water resilience is felt. It became clear through our discussions that for most of the members from the water sector, water resilience came from the continued functioning of the current water sector infrastructure, facilitated by the extant water companies. For me, however, water resilience comes down to people having access to appropriately clean water and waste water treatment, however that comes about, and resilience of ecological systems (including human nodes) to water changes such as flooding, changing salination, and so on. I’ve endeavoured to bring these different viewpoints to the working group meetings and to my work mapping and researching for the final report.</p>
<p>Here comes the fun bit, though. The approach of the working group is participative. At iilab, we will be sharing both the water map and the research when it’s in a more complete state. To help inform both the mapping, the research, and the recommendations for Ofwat, the group has generated a survey for interested parties who might have knowledge or ideas to share with respect to working towards water resilience.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-contribute">How to contribute</h2>
<p>What do you think about water resilience? I’d like to share the survey with you - here’s the agreed wording for doing that:</p>
<p>“The UK Water Resilience Task Force would like your views, please complete this short survey, ideally by mid-August”</p>
<p>Contribute to the work by <a href="https://cranfielduniversity.eu.qualtrics.com/SE/?SID=SV_8BbfGUtYjIfeV6Z">completing the survey, hosted by Cranfield University</a>.</p>
<p>I’m informed that the data policy for the survey is that the anonymised data will be made open source unless individuals make a compelling request to be excluded from that.</p>
<p>And if you’re interested to, you can follow or join the UK Water Resilience <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/groups/UK-Water-Resilience-8310265/about">LinkedIn G</a>roup. You can also email at <script type="text/javascript">
<!--
h='&#x6f;&#102;&#x77;&#x61;&#116;&#46;&#x67;&#x73;&#x69;&#46;&#x67;&#x6f;&#118;&#46;&#x75;&#x6b;';a='&#64;';n='&#114;&#x65;&#x73;&#x69;&#108;&#x69;&#x65;&#110;&#x63;&#x65;&#x63;&#x6f;&#110;&#x73;&#x75;&#108;&#116;&#x61;&#116;&#x69;&#x6f;&#110;';e=n+a+h;
document.write('<a h'+'ref'+'="ma'+'ilto'+':'+e+'" clas'+'s="em' + 'ail">'+e+'<\/'+'a'+'>');
// -->
</script><noscript>&#114;&#x65;&#x73;&#x69;&#108;&#x69;&#x65;&#110;&#x63;&#x65;&#x63;&#x6f;&#110;&#x73;&#x75;&#108;&#116;&#x61;&#116;&#x69;&#x6f;&#110;&#32;&#x61;&#116;&#32;&#x6f;&#102;&#x77;&#x61;&#116;&#32;&#100;&#x6f;&#116;&#32;&#x67;&#x73;&#x69;&#32;&#100;&#x6f;&#116;&#32;&#x67;&#x6f;&#118;&#32;&#100;&#x6f;&#116;&#32;&#x75;&#x6b;</noscript> and join in on Twitter using #resilience.</p>]]></description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2015 00:00:00 UT</pubDate>
    <guid>https://iilab.org/news/2015-07-28-uk-water-resilience.html</guid>
    <dc:creator>iilab</dc:creator>
</item>

    </channel>
</rss>
